‫>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
‫>> یہ ہے CS50 - ہارورڈ یونیورسٹی کی طرف سے ایک تعارف
‫Computer سائنس کے علم کی دنیا
‫اور programming کی art کا.
‫اور میرا نام ہے ڈیوڈ میلن (David Malan)،
‫اور صبح صبح آج میں
‫یہ سوچ کر حیران ہورا رہا تھا کہ آج 20 سال گزر گئے اس دن کو
‫جب میں آخری بار وہاں بیٹھا تھا جہاں آج آپ لوگ ہیں.
‫>> سن 1996 کی بات ہے
‫جب میں اپنی پڑھائی کے دوسرے سال میں تھا،
‫اور پہلی بار CS50 کی کلاس لے رہا تھا.
‫اور مجھ سے بالکل بھی ہمّت نہیں ہوپائی تھی
‫کہ اس course کو پہلے سال میں ہی لے لیتا
‫اسکی ایک وجہ یہ تھی کہ اس وقت
‫Computer سائنس کا نام سن کر  ہی مجھے
‫نیند آنے لگتی تھی
‫میں بچپن سے ہی پڑھاکو student تھا، لیکن
‫پھر بھی کبھی
‫مجھے ایسی چیز میں کوئی دلچسپی نہیں تھی
‫جسے دیکھ کر ایسا لگتا تھا کہ
‫ڈھیر سارے لوگ ہر وقت بس
‫programming ہی کر رہے ہوتے ہیں.
‫>> اور سچ تو یہ ہے کہ مجھے ڈر لگتا تھا.
‫یہ course اور کافی حد تک عموماً Computer سائنس
‫کچھ بدنام سی ہے کہ اس سے دور ہی رہنا چاہییے،
‫وہ بھی اس وجہ سے کہ ہم میں سے کئی لوگ
‫اس سے پوری طرح واقف نہیں ہیں اور
‫اس سے اجنبیت محسوس کرتے ہیں.
‫اور میرا نظریہ تب بدلنا شروع ہوا -- جب اس سال کے fall
‫semester میں میں نے یہ کلاس لینا شروع کی
‫لیکن وہ بھی صرف اس وجہ سے
‫ -- کہ میرے professor
‫میرے سب سے پہلے mentor،
‫برائن کرنیہن (Brian Kernighan)، جو اب Princeton میں ہیں،
‫انہوں نے (grades کی بجائے) صرف pass یا fail
‫ہونے کی اجازت دیدی مجھے
‫اور دراصل، یہی وجہ ہے کہ
‫آج بھی ہم نے یہ اجازت دی ہوئی ہے
‫کہ students اس کلاس میں آر یا پار
‫ہو سکیں.
‫>> خیر، میرے semester کے ختم
‫ہوتے ہوتے یہ بات
‫مجھے سمجھ آگئی کہ یہ اتنی بھی کوئی
‫اجنبی field نہیں ہے.
‫اور پھر مجھے یہ field واقعی میں نہایت ہی
‫powerful لگنے لگی،
‫اور دلچسپ طور پر بعد میں جب
‫میں نے  101 Dramatic Arts اور Latin A
‫کے courses لئے
‫اور پھر جب bachelors کے بعد
‫جب Archeology پڑھی
‫تب کہیں جا کر مجھے احساس ہونا شروع ہوا
‫کہComputer سائنس کس طرح سے
‫humanities سے، natural سائنس، medicine، arts، اور
‫کئی اس طرح کی دوسری fields
‫سے جڑی ہوئی ہے.
‫اور یہی تو Computer سائنس کی سب سے
‫اچھی بات ہے جو
‫ہمیں امید ہے کہ آپ بھی دیکھ لیں گے --
‫کہ کتنا زیادہ کام آسکتی ہے یہ
‫دوسری fields میں بھی، اور کس طرح سے
‫آج کے اور پورے semesters میں بتائے گئے
‫ideas اور practical skills کو آپ
‫اپنی اپنی fields میں لے جا سکیں گے،
‫اور خود یہ سمجھ پائینگے کہ کسی طرح یہ
‫فنونٍ لطیفہ اور سائنس سے جڑی ہوئی ہے.
‫>> اگر پچھلے سال کی کلاس سے اندازہ لگائیں تو
‫آپ لوگوں میں سے بھی 73% لوگوں نے
‫اس سے پہلے کبھی Computer سائنس کا کوئی course نہیں کیا ہوگا.
‫تو، میری طرح، اگر آپ بھی
‫تھوڑا سا
‫ڈرے ہوئے ہیں، یا اگر تھوڑا بے تکلف ہوکر کہوں تو،
‫اگر آپ کو بھی نہیں معلوم آپ نے یہ course کیوں چن لیا ہے.
‫یا شاید آپ اپنے دوستوں کی دیکھا دیکھی
‫میں یہاں آگئے ہیں،
‫تو بھی کوئی مسئلہ نہیں ہے.
‫کہنے کا مقصد یہ کہ آپ کی
‫یہ یقین دہانی کرنی ہے
‫کہ اگر آپ اپنے چاروں طرف دیکھیں
‫تو آپ کے گرد بیٹھے آپ کے classmates
‫کا علم اور تجربہ بھی
‫ آپ سے زیادہ مختلف نہیں ہوگا.
‫اور بعد میں ہم کچھ
‫اعداد و شمار کی بھی بات کرینگے
‫کہ عام طور پر اس کلاس کی
‫demographics کیا رہی ہیں اب تک.
‫>> اور course کے syllabus میں آپ کا اعتماد
‫ -- اور یہ میں اس لئے کہہ رہا ہوں کہ میں نے خود بھی یہ course
‫کچھ سال پہلے لیا تھا -- یہ سن کر
‫بڑھ جانا چاہیے
‫کہ اس course میں
‫سب سے زیادہ اہم بات
‫یہ نہیں ہوگی کہ آپ اپنے classmates سے
‫کتنا آگے نکل پاتے ہیں،
‫بلکہ یہ ہوگی کہ course کے week 11 یعنی آخری week میں
‫آپ اپنے آپ سے کتنا آگے نکل پاتے ہیں،
‫اس week 0 کے مقابلے میں،
‫جہاں ہم آج ہیں.
‫اور اس بات کا احساس مجھے
‫ان گزرے ہوئے سالوں میں ہوا.
‫اور حالانکہ ہر دوسری کلاس میں
‫یہی بات سننے کو ملتی ہے لیکن
‫Computer سائنس کے بارے میں یہ بات اور بھی
‫زیادہ سچ ہے.
‫اور بالآخر، یہ field جو
‫مجھے اتنی عجیب و غریب لگتی تھی
‫اور شاید آپ کو بھی لگتی ہو،
‫اصل میں problems کو solve کرنے کے بارے میں ہے بس.
‫اور یہی تو وجہ ہے کہ یہ اتنی
‫زیادہ کام  آسکتی ہے ہمیں دوسری fields میں بھی.
‫اور اگر ہم اس بات کی
‫گہرائی میں جائیں تو واقعی میں
‫تو اصل میں problems کو solve کرنے
‫کا مطلب کچھ یوں ہے:
‫ایک input ہوتا ہے -- یعنی کچھ بھی ایسا
‫جسے آپ solve کرنے کی کوشش کر رہے ہوتے ہیں .
‫اور ایک output ہوتا ہے، جو کہ ہوتا ہے
‫آپ کی problem کا (حل) solution.
‫اور پھر، جس طرح computer سائنس کی
‫زبان میں کہا جاتا ہے،
‫بیچ میں ایک black box ہوتا ہے
‫جس کے بارے آپ کو
‫یہ جاننے کی ضرورت نہیں کہ یہ کیسے کام کرتا ہے.
‫یہ بھی ہوسکتا ہے کہ اس box کے
‫اندر کی چیزیں آپ خود بنا رہے ہوں.
‫لیکن آج، یا عام طور پر زندگی میں،
‫آپ کو سروکار اس بات سے ہوتا ہے
‫کہ ان problems کو solve کرنا.
‫>> اور اس course کا بنیادی طور پر
‫مقصد ہی
‫یہ سمجھنا ہے کہ inputs اور outputs
‫ایک دوسرے سے کیسے جڑے ہوئے ہیں.
‫اور پھر یہ algorithms،
‫جن کی ہم جلد ہی بات کرینگے،
‫کس طرح پردے کے پیچھے
‫رہ کر سارا کام کر رہے ہوتے ہیں.
‫لیکن یہ inputs اور یہ outputs --
‫ان کا مطلب ہے کیا آخر؟
‫اصل میں ہمیں بالآخر کوئی طریقہ چاہیئے
‫information کو بیان کرنے کا.
‫اور یہ بات Computer پر اور بھی fit آتی ہے،
‫جو ہمیں بھلے ہی جتنا بھی دلکش اور پیچیدہ
‫لگتا ہو، لیکن یہ ہے انتہائی بے عقل device.
‫یہ بجلی سے چلتا ہے -- چاہے پھر
‫کسی تار سے input لے رہا ہو یا battery سے --
‫اور پھر screen پر وہی سب دکھاتا ہے
‫جو پہلے سے اس میں program کر دیا گیا ہے.
‫>> لیکن شروع سے آخر تک
‫یہ سب ہوتا کیسے ہے؟
‫ایک problem کو solve کرنے کی مثال لے لیتے ہیں
‫جیسے کہ، شاید، کسی بھی
‫semester کے شروع میں ہم
‫اس طرح کی کلاس میں attendance
‫لینے کی بات کرتے ہیں.
‫تو شاید میں یوں کر سکتا ہوں، ایک، دو، تین،
‫یا پھر شاید، اگر میں اسی طرح
‫انگلیوں پر
‫گنتا رہا -- تو دس کے بعد پھر میرے لئے
‫چیزوں کو  یاد رکھنا مشکل ہوجاۓ گا.
‫تو اس لئے ایک طریقہ ہے لکیریں کھینچنے کا --
‫ایک بندہ، دو، تین، چار، پانچ، چھ،
‫سات، آٹھ
‫اور  ہم سبھی نے ہی تقریباً اس طرح کیا
‫ہوگا، چاہے اپنے ہاتھوں پر،
‫یا کسی کاغذ پر.
‫اور یہ جو  طریقہ ہے، اسے ہم
‫اصل میںUnary (اُونیری) notation کہتے ہیں.
‫جس میں ہمارے پاس صرف ایک symbol  ہوتا ہے،
‫یعنی 1 کا یا پھر hash (#) کا نشان،
‫جیسا کہ اس مثال میں تھا.
‫ہر ایک input کو گننے کے لئے
‫آپ ان میں سے کوئی symbol -- کوئی
‫نشان لگاتے ہیں.
‫>> خیر
‫اب تک تو ہم نے مشکل کی بجائے صرف
‫آسان آسان باتیں کیں.
‫لیکن computers کو سمجھنا بھی
‫اب تک کی باتوں سے زیادہ مشکل نہیں ہے.
‫اور چاہے آپ نے کبھی اس چیز
‫کے مطلب کے بارے میں نہ بھی سوچا ہو
‫لیکن تقریباً آپ سب کو ہی یہ معلوم
‫ہوگا کہ Computers صرف zeros (صفر)
‫اور ones (ایک) کو سمجھ سکتے ہیں --
‫جسے ہم binary (بائینری) system کہتے ہیں.
‫ہم انسان، اس کے برعکس، کہیں زیادہ
‫sophisticated ہیں
‫کیونکہ ہم zero سے لیکر nine تک کو سمجھ پاتے ہیں.
‫>> اور حالانکہ بھلے ہی binary ہمیں
‫ہمیں عجیب و غریب لگتا ہو
‫لیکن ہقیقتاً یہ system اور اس کے اصول
‫بھی ہمارے decimal system کی طرح ہی ہیں.
‫مثلاّ، یہ دیکھیں
‫یہ بس symbols کی ایک sequence ہے.
‫اور آپ سب اس پر
‫نظریں جمائے ہوئے شاید
‫یہ سوچ رہے ہوں: ایک سو تیس (123) --
‫اس میں ایسا خاص کیا ہے.
‫لیکن یہ نمبر 123 کیوں ہے؟
‫یہ screen پر بس کچھ لکیریں
‫ماری ہوئی ہیں -- یہ کچھ خاکے ہیں
‫جو کسی نے بنا دیئے ہیں.
‫لیکن اگر آپ میری طرح ہیں
‫تو آپ نے یقیناً school میں پڑھا ہوگا
‫کہ یہ اصل میں columns ہیں،
‫numbers کی places ہیں
‫سب سے پہلے ones (یا units) کی place،
‫پھر tens کی place، اور پھر hundreds کی.
‫اور اگر یہ صرف و صرف 3 بے معنی لکریروں کے خاکے
‫ہونے کی بجائے ایک سو تیس (123) ہے تو
‫اس وجہ کہ یہ ہے کہ یہاں hundreds
‫کی place میں 1 لکھا ہے
‫تھوڑی سی Math لگائیں تو مطلب سو ہے ایک بار.
‫اور پھر tens کی place میں 2 ہے.
‫یعنی کہ دو بار دس، اور پھر ہے 3
‫جو کہ ones کی place میں ہے یعنی ایک بار 3.
‫اور جب آپ ان سب کو add کردیں، تو
‫یقیناً یہ بنتا ہے 100+20+3.
‫>> تو شروع ہم نے symbols کے patterns
‫سے کیا -- ایک alphabet سے --
‫لیکن پھر ہر symbol کو ایک place دے کر ہم نے
‫ہم نے انہیں معنی خیز بنا دیا.
‫خیر، Computers بھی اصل میں
‫مجھ سے یا آپ سے
‫بالکل بھی مختلف نہیں ہیں.
‫لیکن 10 کی powers
‫- یعنی 1, 10, 100, 1000
‫10,000 وغیرہ کی places کو
‫use کرنے کی بجائے
‫Computers دو (2) کی powers کو use
‫کرتے ہیں -- یعنی 2، 4، وغیرہ
‫اور اگر تھوڑے اور digits لے لیں، تو
‫8, 16, 64, 128, وغیرہ
‫تو Computer کچھ اس طرح سے
‫represent کریگا نمبر zero کو
‫بالکل جیسے ہم کرتے ہیں.
‫>> 0, 0, 0 -- اور آپ آسانی سے
‫guess کرسکتے ہیں کہ zeros اور ones کیا pattern --
‫اگر computer صرف 0  یا 1
‫کی زبان بولتا ہے -- تو کس
‫pattern کے ذریعے وہ اس نمبر کو
‫represent کریگا جسے ہم لوگ One (ایک) کہتے ہیں.
‫بالکل -- 1, 0, 0
‫All right
‫تو اگر 1 (ایک) کو ہم 0, 0,
‫1, کرکے ظاہر کیا جائے گا، تو پھر
‫نمبر 2 کو کیسے ظاہر کرینگے.
‫اگر یہ ہے Four's کی place، اور یہ Two's کی place
‫اور یہ Ones کی place، تو آپ simply کہہ سکتے ہیں
‫کہ ہم Ones کی place میں 1 لگا دینگے.
‫اور اب ہم آپ 2 (دو) لکھنے کی
‫بات کریں تو شاید آپ
‫یہاں 1 لگا دیں، اور یہاں zero.
‫لیکن اصل میں یہ طریقہ تو ہمارے decimal (دس کے)
‫system میں بھی غلط ہوگا.
‫کیونکہ اگر آپ ہر digit کو اس کی place سے
‫multiply کردیں،
‫اور تھوڑا دماغ لگائیں،
‫تو 2 کی بجائے میں نے کونسا نمبر
‫غلطی سے لکھ دیا ہے یہاں؟
‫>> یہ 3 (تین) ہے، کیوںکہ 2 بار 1
‫+ 1 کرکے ہمیں 3 ملتا ہے.
‫تو 2 اصل میں کچھ یوں ہوگا.
‫یہ bit ایک لحاظ سے flip ہوگیا، 0 سے 1
‫بننے پر، بالکل جس طرح 9 کے بعد گنتی دوبارہ
‫0 پر چلی جاتی ہے، اور 1 آگے بڑھ کر
‫دس بن جاتا ہے.
‫اور 3 پھر کچھ اس طرح سے ہوگا.
‫چار (4) -- ایک اور دلچسپ چیز ہوگی اب
‫جب یہ ones دونوں 0 بن جائیں گے،
‫اور 1 آگے بڑھ جائے گا.
‫اور اس طرح یہ ہے 4 (چار).
‫>> لیکن اب اگر تھوڑا jump کریں تو
‫سب سے بڑا نمبر کونسا ہوگا جو
‫جو computer ان تین bits (یعنی digits) میں ظاہر کرسکے گا؟
‫
‫تو اس کا جواب ہے 7 (سات)، right ؟
‫کیونکہ 4s کی place میں 1 ہے،
‫اور 2s اور 1s کی place میں بھی 1 ہے.
‫یعنی 4+2+1
‫یعنی کہ 7 (سات).
‫اور ابھی ایسا لگےگا کہ
‫Computer سات سے آگے گنتی
‫نہیں کرسکتا.
‫>> لیکن اصل میں یہ سچ نہیں ہے.
‫کیونکہ ہم کیا کرتے ہیں جب ہمیں گنتی کو
‫999 سے آگے بڑھانا ہوتا ہے؟
‫
‫ہم left پر ایک اور digit لگا کر
‫1 کو اس چوتھے digit پر لکھ دیتے ہیں.
‫تو computer بھی اسی طرح سے
‫Eights کی place اور 16s کی place کو
‫use کر سکتے ہیں.
‫اور 32s کی place، اور 64، 128 --
‫مطلب آپ کتنا بھی آگے جا سکتے ہیں.
‫-- تو اس binary system میں --
‫ان ones اور zeros کو
‫Computer کے سائنسدان binary
‫digits یا short میں bits کہتے ہیں.
‫>> لیکن اب، اس پورے concept اور
‫اس 1s اور  0s کے قصّے کہانی کا
‫ایک اصل computer سے کیا تعلق؟
‫یہاں ہم نے ایک چیز کی تو بات ہی نہیں کی.
‫Well، میرے laptop کو  بالآخر جو input ملتا ہے
‫وہ ہے بجلی !
‫بھلے ہی آپ نے کافی عرصے سے
‫اس بارے میں نہ سوچا ہو
‫یا کبھی بھی نہ سوچا ہو کہ
‫بجلی کیسے کام کرتی ہے،
‫تو یہ اصل میں electrons کا flow ہوتا ہے،
‫جسے میں ایک لحاظ سے input کہوں گا.
‫>> تو laptop کو صرف یہی input مل
‫رہا ہے -- یعنی بجلی --
‫تو اب اس information (یعنی input) کے ساتھ
‫ہم کیا کیا کر سکتے ہیں؟
‫Well، بجلی کے نہ ہونے کو ہم
‫بالکل zero کی طرح سوچ سکتے ہیں.
‫نہ بجلی آ رہی ہے، نہ electrons کی movement ہے،
‫یعنی کچھ بھی نہیں ہو رہا.
‫تو یہ simply ایک default حالت ہے --  0 (zero).
‫لیکن جب بجلی flow کررہی ہوتی ہے، تو کیوں نہ
‫ہم سب مل ایسا کریں کہ اپنی مرضی سے
‫اس حالت کو 1 (one) کا نام دے دیں.
‫>> تو simply جب بھی بجلی نہیں ہوگی،
‫تو ہم کہیں گے zero، اور جب بجلی ہوگی
‫تو ہم کہیں گے one --
‫بجلی ہے، بجلی نہیں ہے.
‫اور اس طرح سے ہم کسی physical یا
‫electronic چیزوں کو لے کر
‫ہم اب اس بات کو سمجھ سکتے ہیں کہ
‫one یا zero ہونے کا کیا مطلب بنتا ہے.
‫اور یہ ہم یہاں پر کرکے بھی دیکھ سکتے ہیں.
‫تو یہاں ہمارے پاس، تین نہیں، بلکہ آٹھ
‫light کے bulbs ہیں، جس میں سے ہر ایک کا
‫اپنا ایک الگ switch ہے.
‫>> تو یہاں اگر مجھے نمبر 7 (سات) کو
‫represent کرنا ہو تو،
‫میں ان تین lights کو on کردونگا.
‫اور میرے اس computer کے اندر بھی
‫اصل میں لاکھوں،
‫کروڑوں نہایت ہی چھوٹے چھوٹے
‫transistors ہیں جو کہ
‫switches ہوتے ہیں جو on یا off ہو سکتے ہیں.
‫تو یہ والے نسبتاً بہت بڑے switches ہیں --
‫میرے laptop کے اندر
‫بہت ہی ڈھیر سارے switches ہیں.
‫-- لیکن یہ سب ایک ہی کام کرتے ہیں --
‫کسی چیز کو on، یا off کرنا.
‫تو اس طرح computer، ان لاکھوں
‫کروڑوں transistors کے ذریعے
‫ڈھیر سارے zeros اور ones کو
‫represent کرسکتا ہے.
‫اور پھر اس میں وہ hardware بھی ہوتا ہے،
‫جو اس information کو لمبے عرصے تک بھی store کرسکتا ہے.
‫تاکہ جب laptop کو بند بھی کردیں،
‫وہ information ضائع نہ ہو.
‫لیکن اس کی کہانی کسی اور دن سنیں گے.
‫>> تو اب ان bits کے ساتھ ہم کیا کرسکتے ہیں؟
‫اب میں تھوڑا relax کرتا ہوں --
‫اور آپ میں سے کوئی یہاں ایک demo
‫دینا پسند کریگا؟
‫میں نے ان کا ہاتھ سب سے پہلے دیکھا.
‫کیا نام ہے آپ کا؟
‫ماڈے
‫اوپر آجائیں، ماڈے!
‫Nice to meet you.
‫MADAY: Nice to meet you.
‫>> یہاں آجائیں.
‫تاکہ مجھے آپ کو اوپر نہ کھینچنا پڑے.
‫All right.
‫تو یہ دیکھیں، یہاں ہمارے پاس ہے -- 1، 2 --
‫دوبارہ سے کرتے ہیں -- 1، 2، 4،
‫8، 16، 32، 64، 128
‫اور سوچ سمجھ کر
‫یہاں 8 (آٹھ) bits ہیں -- binary digits --
‫zeros اور ones
‫-- اور bit ایک useful طریقہ ہے ناپنے کا --
‫خیر اتنا بھی useful نہیں ہوگا اگر
‫صرف ایک bit ہی ہو تو.
‫عموماً، ہم کم از کم 8 (آٹھ) bits کی
‫بات کرتے ہیں، جسے ہم
‫1 (ایک) byte کہتے ہیں.
‫تو یہاں ہمارے پاس 8 bits سے بنا ایک byte ہے.
‫>> تو اگر میں آپ کو ایک challenge دوں
‫جیسے کہ، آپ کو binary میں
‫یہ value لکھنی ہے -- 42
‫کیا آپ یہ challenge لینا چاہینگی؟
‫>> MADAY: [INAUDIBLE].
‫آپ کو بس وہ آگے لگے ہوئے white
‫switch دبانے ہونگے.
‫اور آپ کو 42 بنا کر دکھانا ہے،
‫اور انعام کے طور پر
‫آپ کو CS50 کا یہ stress ball ملیگا،
‫اگر آپ نے  یہ کرلیا.
‫All right
‫تو آپ نے 32 بنا لیا.
‫ہمیں 42 بنانا ہے اسے
‫تو یہ اٹھ (8) بھی ہوگی، جو ہوگیا 40.
‫اور زبردست -- بہت خوب.
‫Thank you.
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫All right
‫تو ہمارے پاس ایک اور stress ball ہے.
‫ایک بار پھر سے کر سکتے ہیں ہم یہ.
‫کوئی اور آنا چاہیگا؟
‫Stress ball ملیگا مفت میں.
‫OK.
‫وہ بیچ میں سے،
‫آپ آنا چاہیںگے؟
‫All right.
‫I know.
‫There we go.
‫>> جو نمبر آپ کو --
‫آجائیں.
‫نام کیا ہے آپ کا؟
‫>> Davey (ڈیوی)
‫>> Davey
‫OK
‫اوپر آجائیں، Davey
‫Nice to meet you
‫اور آپ کو جو نمبر میں دوں گا --
‫اگر آپ تھوڑا سا صبر کریں
‫کچھ seconds کیلئے --
‫وہ ہے نمبر 50.
‫لیکن، لیکن، لیکن، لیکن، لیکن،
‫یہ fridge والے magnets اس لئے تو لگائے تھے.
‫
‫تھوڑا سا مشکل بنا دیا، ہے نا؟
‫ابھی بھی یہ 8 ہی ہیں.
‫
‫All right.
‫تو وہ والا کونسا ہے؟
‫وہ ہے 32.
‫Nice.
‫plus سولہ (16)، جس سے اب یہ 48 ہوگیا --
‫بہت ہی قریب ہیں.
‫اور بہت ہی عمدہ.
‫Davey کو بھی stress ball مبارک ہو.
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫>> All right
‫تو ہم یہ پورا دن کر سکتے ہیں،
‫لیکن پھر ایک وقت آئیگا جب
‫ہم سب اس سے bore ہوجائیں گے.
‫لیکن یہی تو مقصد ہے سمجھانے کا --
‫کہ اس اتنے simple سے طریقے سے
‫Computer بالآخر ساری information
‫کو store کرتا ہے.
‫چاہے input کی information ہو یا
‫output کی، اسی طرح represent ہوتی ہے.
‫لیکن صرف و صرف numbers کو
‫store کرکے اتنا مزہ نہیں آئیگا.
‫>> تو انسانوں نے اس لئے کچھ سال پہلے
‫کیا طے کیا، پتا ہے آپ کو؟
‫کہ مزے کی بات تو تب ہوگی جب
‫computers نہ صرف
‫numbers کی calculations کر سکیں
‫بلکہ اس کے علاوہ بھی
‫الفاظ لکھنا، emails، اور
‫دوسری اس ہی طرح کی modern
‫چیزیں بھی کرسکیں.
‫تو دنیا میں ہم سب نے اپنی مرضی
‫سے، متفقہ طور پہ، یہ طے کیا
‫کہ ہمیں اگر computer میں capital
‫A کو store کرنا ہے تو آج سے پھر
‫اسے store کرنے کیلئے، ہم سب
‫zeros اور ones -- یعنی bits کا
‫ ایک ہی طرح کا pattern استعمال کریں گے --
‫جو decimal میں بنتا ہے 65.
‫اور ہم سب لوگ اس پر متفق ہونگے.
‫>> اسی طرح 66 ہوگا ہمارا B، اور
‫67 ہوگا ہوگا ہمارا C.
‫اور اسی طرح سے کئی دوسرے zeros اور ones کے
‫patterns، یعنی numbers کو،
‫ہم دوسرے alphabets کو represent
‫کرنے کیلئے استعمال کرینگے.
‫تو اگر آپ اس تھوڑی دیر کیلئے اپنے
‫ذہن میں بٹھانے کی کوشش کریں،
‫میں نے جان بوجھ کر وہاں A سے لے کر I
‫تک لکھا ہے، جہاں H اصل میں 72 ہے، اور I
‫73 ہے.
‫اگر computer کسی Word Processing
‫(الفاظ لکھانے والے) software یا پھر email میں
‫ان دیئے ہوئے numbers -- ان bits کے
‫patterns کو
‫store کر رہا ہو -- 72, پھر 73,
‫اور پھر 33 --
‫تو وہ program کس لفظ کو store کر رہا ہوگا؟
‫>> اس کا جواب ہے HI، اور
‫پھر آگے کچھ اور.
‫شاید ہمیں سمجھ نہ آئے لیکن 33 اصل میں --
‫جو کہ chart پر موجود نہیں تھا --
‫ایک exclamation
‫mark (!) ہے.
‫تو 72 جو ہے وہ ہے H، پھر 73 ہے I، اور
‫پھر جو 33 ہے وہ ہے exclamation mark (!).
‫لیکن یہ تو سب تو ٹھیک ہے،
‫اور دراصل آج کل ہم، بجائے اس کے کہ
‫سات یا آٹھ bits استعمال کریں، اب ہم
‫جیسا کہ گزرے سالوں میں ASCII (ایسکی)
‫use کرتے تھے، اب ہم Unicode کو use کرتے ہیں
‫جس کے ذریعے ہم بہت سارے دوسرے
‫دلچسپ characters کو represent کر سکتے ہیں
‫مثلاّ دوسری زبانوں کے alphabets.
‫لیکن ہم اور بھی  بہتر چیزوں کو
‫represent کرسکتے ہیں، جیسا کہ colors کو.
‫>> اگر آپ نے کبھی RGB کا نام سنا ہو،
‫یعنی blue، green، red تو اس کا
‫مطلب یہ ہے کہ computer اصل میں
‫bits کے تین sets کو use کرتا ہے --
‫bits کا ایک set ( یعنی نمبر) یہ بتاتا ہے
‫کہ لال رنگ کتنا زیادہ ہے،
‫bits کا ایک دوسرا set ہمیں green
‫کی مقدار کا بتاتا ہے.
‫اور پھر ایک اور set (نمبر) ہمیں
‫blue رنگ کے بارے میں بتاتا ہے.
‫تو بڑے نمبر کا مطلب بہت زیادہ red،
‫اور چھوٹے نمبر کا مطلب کہ بالکل بھی red نہیں.
‫اور یہ کچھ بیچ کی values
‫لی ہیں یہاں پر.
‫>> تو اگر میں تھوڑا red لے لوں، اور تھوڑا سا
‫green، اور معمولی سا blue تو
‫اور اب اگر ان تینوں shades کو mix کردوں،
‫تو پھر ہمارے پاس
‫یہ گدلا سا yellow یا brown
‫type کا color آجائیگا.
‫لیکن یہ جو pattern ہے آٹھ plus
‫آٹھ plus آٹھ -- یعنی 24 bits --
‫left سے right، اس طریقے سے ہی اصل میں
‫computer کسی بھی color کو represent کرتا ہے.
‫اور یہ اصل میں صرف ایک dot ہوتا ہے screen پر.
‫اگر آپ TV یا Computer کو نہایت ہی قریب سے
‫دیکھیں، تو آپ کو dots یا pixels نظر آئیں گے.
‫اور اگر آپ pixels کی پوری grid لے لیں،
‫اوپر سے نیچے اور دائیں سے بائیں،
‫تو اس سے images (تصویریں) بن جائیں گی.
‫اور اگر آپ ایک image لے،
‫اور پھر اسے ہٹا کر
‫ایک اور image لے آئیں، پھر ایک اور image،
‫پھر ایک اور image، اور ایک اور image،
‫اور نہایت ہی تیزی سے کریں،
‫تو یہ بن جائینگی movies.
‫>> تو اب ذرا غور کریں کہ ہم نے
‫شروعات کیسے کی تھی.
‫ہم نے zeros اور ones سے شروعات کی.
‫پھر وہاں سے ہوتے ہوئے ہم نے دیکھا کہ decimal
‫numbers کو کس طرح represent کیا جاتا ہے.
‫اب ہم letters یعنی alphabets پر آگئے.
‫لیکن اگر اپنا رخ تھوڑا موڑیں، تو ہم تھوڑےسے اور
‫bits لا کر colors کو represent کر سکتے ہیں.
‫اور جیسے ہی ہمارے پاس colors کو
‫represent کرنے کی صلاحیت آگئی،
‫تو اب آپ photographs اور animated
‫gif (یعنی animated تصویروں) کو،
‫اور اسی طرح کی دوسری چیزوں کو
‫screen پر represent کر سکتے ہیں.
‫اور اگر ڈھیر ساری تیزی سے بدلتی ہوئی images
‫کو لے کر کس انسان کو دکھائیں،
‫تو اسے یہ motion pictures لگینگی،
‫اور اس طرح ہمارے پاس videos بھی آگئیں.
‫>> تو ان انتہائی simple اور
‫بنیادی چیزوں کو ذریعے
‫ہم information کی ان تمام اقسام
‫کو represent کر سکتے ہیں.
‫تو ہم نے سب سے چھوٹے level (یعنی bits)
‫سے شروع کیا اور وہاں سے کرتے کرتے
‫ہم سب سے اوپر کے level (videos وغیرہ)
‫پر آگئے.
‫تو اس سے ہمیں اندازہ ہوجاتا ہے کہ کس طرح
‫نچلے levels کو جوڑ جوڑ کر ہم اوپر تک آسکتے ہیں.
‫لیکن ہم یہاں سے شروع کیا تھا.
‫>> اور یہاں ہم computer میں
‫اپنے inputs اور اپنے outputs کو
‫دونوں کو zeros اور ones کے ذریعے
‫represent کر سکتے ہیں.
‫لیکن اب اس box کے اندر کیا ہو رہا ہوتا ہے؟
‫اور یہیں computer سائنس بہت
‫interesting بن جاتی ہے.
‫یہیں پر آپ خود اپنا دماغ لگا کر problems
‫کو solve کرنے کی کوشش کرتے ہیں.
‫اور یہاں اب ایک شرط یہ ہوگی
‫اس پورے semester کے لئے کہ
‫آپ کو معلوم ہو کہ binary کیسے کام کرتا ہے.
‫اور آپ کو ASCII یا Unicode کا یاد ہو --
‫کہ یہ alphabets سے کس طرح جڑے ہیں.
‫اورساتھ ہی یہ بھی یاد رہے کہ binary سے
‫red اور green اور blue اور باقی multimedia
‫کو represent کیا جا سکتا ہے.
‫لیکن اصل interesting چیز تو یہ ہے.
‫یہ وہ چیز ہے جس سے کسی کو بھی
‫problems کو solve کرنا آپ پاتا ہے.
‫>> اور اسی طرح کی ایک problem،
‫جس کو ابھی ہم حل کرنے کوشش کرینگے،
‫وہ ہے attendance (حاضری) لینا، بلکہ
‫algorithm کی ذریعے attendance لینا.
‫اور پہلے کی طرح، میں یہ کر سکتا ہوں.
‫ایک، دو، تین، چار، پانچ،
‫چھ، سات، آٹھ، نو.
‫اور یاد رکھنے کے لئے میں
‫اسے لکھ بھی سکتا ہوں.
‫لیکن یہ بس ایک طریقہ ہے information
‫کو represent کرنے کا.
‫یا پھر تھوڑا تیزی سے کچھ ہوں کرسکتا ہوں --
‫2، 4، 6، 8، 10، 12، 14، 16، 18، 20،
‫22 -- تو اس طرح میری speed تو
‫double ہوگئی، لیکن ابھی بھی
‫بہت زیادہ time لگےگا.
‫>> لیکن اسے ہم ایک اور ذریعے سے بھی
‫کر سکتے ہیں -- اور دراصل computers میں
‫آج کل multiple (یعنی ایک سے زیادہ)
‫processors یا brains ہوتے ہیں.
‫یعنی کہ computer کئی سارے کام
‫ایک ہی وقت میں کر سکتا ہے،
‫اور ہم بھی اس کلاس میں کچھ ایسا ہی
‫کرنے کی کوشش کرسکتے ہیں.
‫>> تو شاید آپ اپنے پڑوسی سے بات نہ
‫کرنا چاہتے ہوں، لیکن میری خوشی کیلئے
‫آپ اس تین steps کے process میں میرا ساتھ دیں،
‫اور میں آپ سب سے گزارش کرونگا کہ
‫آپ سب کھڑے ہوجائیں تھوڑی دیر کیلئے.
‫Stand up
‫اب آپ نمبر 1 کو ذہن میں رکھ لیں --
‫تو اس کلاس میں ہر کوئی اس وقت،
‫سواۓ ان لوگوں کے جو کھڑے نہیں ہوئے،
‫وہ سب 1 کے بارے میں سوچ رہے ہیں.
‫تو یہ آپ کا نمبر ہے اس وقت.
‫یہ پہلا step ہے، یا جیسا کہ ایک computer
‫scientist یا ایک programmer
‫عام طور پر کرتا ہے، ہم  بھی
‫zero سے گنتی شروع کرینگے.
‫اگر ان light کے bulbs سے جو سب سے
‫چھوٹا نمبر ہم represent کرسکتے ہیں
‫وہ ہے 0، simply سب bulbs کو off کرکے،
‫اسی طرح ہم بھی
‫1 کی بجائے 0 سے گنتی شروع کرسکتے ہیں.
‫اور computer کے scientists بھی یہی کرتے ہیں.
‫تو Step نمبر 0 ہے، کھڑے ہوجائیں،
‫اور 1 کے بارے میں سوچیں.
‫اگلا step کچھ یوں ہے -- اپنے برابر میں
‫کھڑے کسی کے ساتھ جوڑی بنایئں،
‫آپس میں اپنا نمبر add کر لیں.
‫
‫Wonderful
‫>> تو اس وقت تقریبا سبھی کھڑے ہوئے لوگ
‫اس وقت نمبر 2 کے بارے میں سوچ رہے ہیں،
‫سوائے اس ایک بیچارے بندے کے، جس کے ساتھ
‫جوڑی بنانے کیلئے کوئی بچا نہیں.
‫اور تیسرا step کچھ یوں ہونے والا ہے --
‫آپ میں سے کوئی ایک بیٹھ جاۓ.
‫آپ میں سے کوئی ایک بیٹھ جاۓ،
‫اور اگر آپ ابھی بھی کھڑے ہیں،
‫تو step نمبر 1 سے دوبارہ شروع کریں.
‫
‫All right
‫اور زیادہ سے زیادہ لوگوں کو
‫بیٹھتے جانا چاہیئے.
‫دیکھیں یہاں ایک loop (چکّر) شروع ہوگیا ہے --
‫ایک طرح کا cycle
‫آپ سے کچھ لوگ اب بھی اس پریشانی میں
‫پھنسے ہیں، اور بار بار پہلے step پر دوہرا رہے ہیں.
‫اور 2، اور 1 اور 2، اور 1 اور 2
‫
‫That's OK.
‫ہمارا پہلا bug (مسئلہ)
‫خیر ہم دیکھ لیں گے اسے.
‫All right
‫چلیں آپ کی تھوڑی مدد کردیتا ہوں.
‫>> اصولاً، صرف ایک ہی شخص رہ جاتا ہے،
‫جب باقی کے لوگ جوڑی بنا لیتے ہیں.
‫لیکن چلیں جو کھڑے ہوئے ہیں
‫ان کو تیزی سے نپٹاتے ہیں.
‫آپ کونسا نمبر سوچ رہے ہیں؟
‫46
‫OK
‫ٹھیک ہے، اب آپ بیٹھ جائیں.
‫آپ لوگ اب بھی کھڑے ہوۓ ہیں.
‫اب تک اور کون کھڑا ہوا ہے؟
‫آپ کیا نمبر سوچ رہے ہیں؟
‫OK
‫>> تو آپ کی طرح دوبارہ آئیں گے.
‫پیچھے وہاں؟
‫کیا کہا آپ نے؟
‫22
‫OK، اوپر سے کوئی -- جی؟
‫34.
‫OK.
‫میرے right پر، یہاں اوپر؟
‫بہت خوب، 132.
‫22
‫>> OK
‫اور کون کھڑا ہے اب تک؟
‫یہاں پر؟
‫بہت خوب، 46.
‫72
‫میں اور برداشت نہیں کر سکتا.
‫جی؟
‫30، nice.
‫یہاں پر؟
‫23؟
‫23
‫>> اور میرے خیال سے اب سب لوگ ہوگئے،
‫سواۓ آپ لوگوں کے، کوئی مسئلہ نہیں.
‫Oh, wait
‫28؟
‫
‫صرف 8.
‫OK
‫وہاں پر؟
‫اس algorithm اس سے زیادہ برے
‫طریقہ سے کبھی implement نہیں کیا.
‫OK
‫کوئی اور بچا ہے اب؟
‫ہے کوئی؟
‫OK
‫ایک اور.
‫16؟
‫OK
‫16
‫All right
‫اگر اب کوئی رہ نہیں گیا ہے تو
‫اب جب میں enter دباؤں گا.
‫اس algorithm کے طریقے سے ہم دیکھیں گے
‫ کہ اس Sanders hall میں کتنے لوگ موجود ہیں.
‫اور یاد رہے کہ جیسے ہی آپ بیٹھتے گئے
‫تو دوسروں نے آپ کا نمبر کسی اور آگے پہنچایا
‫اور اسنے کسی اور کو، اور کسی اور نے
‫کسی اور کو، تو اس طرح اصولاً،
‫آخر میں  صرف وہ ایک عجیب سا بندہ
‫کھڑا رہ گیا.
‫لیکن کوئی بات نہیں.
‫اور بیچ میں ہم نے تھوڑی تیزی دکھائی.
‫اور screen دیکھ پانا تھوڑا سا مشکل
‫اس lighting کی وجہ سے.
‫>> اور اس کلاس میں لوگوں کی total
‫تعداد ہمارے خیال سے جو ہے وہ ہے 545.
‫میرے teaching fellows نے جو
‫تعداد مجھے بتائی تھی
‫جو انھیں پرانے اور slow طریقے سے
‫گنی تھی، وہ تھی 820.
‫>> [LAUGHING]
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫>> That's OK
‫جسکا مطلب یہ کہ ہمارے
‫algorithm میں bugs تھے.
‫لیکن کوئی مسئلہ نہیں.
‫اور اگر آپ اس پر تھوڑا سوچیں
‫تو پہلی بار میں کوئی بھی چیز
‫ضروری نہیں کہ صحیح سے کام کر جائے.
‫اور یہ میرے ساتھ بھی ہوتا ہے یہاں.
‫لیکن چلیں اب یہ دیکھتے ہیں کہ ہم
‫اس ہی idea کو ایک ایسی چیز پر
‫جو آپ نے دیکھی ہی ہوگی،اسے کیسے apply
‫کرسکتے ہیں -- جو کہ ہے یہ پرانے زمانے کی
‫وہ بھی بڑی phone book.
‫اور میرے خیال سے اس phone
‫book میں 1000 pages اور 1000 نام،
‫اور 1000 phone نمبر ہونگے ناموں کی ترتیب میں.
‫>> ہم اس سے کچھ بالکل ملتا جلتا idea اس physical
‫problem پر بھی apply کر سکتے ہیں.
‫صرف مجھے use کرکے.
‫میں نے ایک لحاظ سے آپ سب لوگوں کو
‫trick کیا تھا آپ سب  کے ڈھیر سارے
‫دماغوں یا CPUs کا فائدہ اٹھا کر، ایک ہی algorithm کو
‫execute کرنے (یعنی چلانے) کا کہہ کر.
‫لیکن اگر صرف مجھ اکیلے کمزور
‫بندے کو یہ کرنا پڑے، تو ابھی بھی
‫میں بالکل اس ہی divide اور rule کے
‫idea کا فائدہ بار بار اٹھا سکتا ہوں
‫جس میں، آپ لوگ ادھے سے ادھے سے
‫آدھے ہوتے گئے،
‫اور اصولاً، بیٹھتے گئے، جب تک
‫ہمارے پاس آخر میں، اصولاً،
‫صرف ایک شخص نہیں بچ گیا.
‫>> تو اس پرانے زمانے کی
‫technology میں -- اور ہمیں اس
‫اس نقشے کی ضرورت نہیں -- اس
‫پرانے زمانے کی technology میں
‫ہمیں کسی بندے کا نام، جیسے Mike
‫Smith ڈھونڈنا ہو، ایک ایک پیج پلٹ کر.
‫اور میں دیکھ رہا ہوں کہ نہیں،
‫Mike یہاں نہیں ہے.
‫میں ابھی بھی A والے section میں ہوں.
‫اور اس طرح کرتے کرتے میں  B
‫section میں آگیا.
‫اور یہ ایک algorithm ہے -- جس میں
‫step-by-step ہدایت (instruction) کو follow کرنا ہے.
‫پہلے page سے شروع کرکے ایک ایک page
‫پر Mike Smith کو ڈھونڈنا ہے.
‫کیا یہ طریقہ یا algorithm صحیح
‫صحیح ہے؟
‫>> ہاں، یہ صحیح طریقہ ہے.
‫اگر Mike کا نام یہاں ہوگا
‫تو بالآخر مجھے مل جائے گا.
‫لیکن یہ efficient (مؤثر) طریقہ نہیں ہے.
‫کیونکہ obviously یہ بہت slow ہے.
‫تو پھر میں وہی ہر دو دو page ایک ساتھ
‫پلٹنے والا طریقہ اپنا سکتا ہوں.
‫میں کچھ یوں کر سکتا ہوں،
‫2، 4، 6، 8، 10، 12.
‫میری speed اب double ہوگئی.
‫اب میں زیادہ تیزی سے Mike کو
‫ڈھونڈ لونگا اگر وہ یہاں ہوا.
‫کیا یہ طریقہ صحیح ہے؟
‫صحیح ہے؟ مجھے ہلکی سی
‫"نہیں" کی آواز آئی ابھی.
‫اب میں نے "نہیں" سنا.
‫جی ہاں.
‫اس طریقے میں ایک bug (مسئلہ) ہے.
‫کیا پتہ Mike کا نام دو pages کے
‫درمیان موجود ہو.
‫اور دو دو page پلٹتے پلٹتے غلطی سے
‫اسکا نام میری نظر سے بچ جائے.
‫تو کم از کم اب ہمیں ایک condition (شرط)
‫رکھ کے اس کو صحیح کرنا ہے.
‫اور مجھے کہنا پڑیگا، کہ جناب
‫اگر مجھے کوئی ایسا نام نظر آیا
‫جو S (یعنی Smith) کی بجائے T سے شروع ہوتا ہو،
‫تو کم از کم اس صورت میں، میں دو دو pages پلٹونگا.
‫تو طریقہ buggy (مسئلے والا) تھا،
‫لیکن صحیح کر لیا ہم نے.
‫لیکن، ہم میں سے کوئی بھی Mike Smith کو
‫اس 1000 page کی phone book میں
‫ایک ایک page پلٹ کر نہیں ڈھونڈیگا.
‫تو ایک normal بندہ پھر کیا کریگا؟
‫اگر آپکو پتہ ہو کہ S والے نام کہاں ہیں تو
‫آپ S والے ناموں میں جائیں گے،
‫اور S والے ناموں کے تقریباً بیچ میں یا
‫شاید تھوڑا آخر کے ناموں میں جائیں گے.
‫اور میں  اس book کی طرف دیکھوں
‫تو میں ابھی M والے section میں ہوں.
‫لیکن ایسا کیا ہے جو اب ہمیں معلوم
‫ہو چکا ہے اس problem کے بارے میں،
‫جو شاید ہمیں پہلے نہیں معلوم تھا جب
‫ہم سب ایک ایک page پلٹ کر دیکھ رہے تھے؟
‫
‫وہ یہ کہ Mike کا نام book کے اس
‫والے آدھے حصّے میں ہونا چاہیئے.
‫اور وہ اس لئے کہ اس book میں
‫سارے نام ترتیب سے لکھے گئے ہیں.
‫>> تو اب آپ بڑے ڈرامائی انداز میں --
‫>> [GASPING]
‫>> ہیں نا.
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫>> دراصل یہ بڑا ہی آسان ہے اگر
‫آپ book کے بالکل بیچ سے یہ کریں.
‫لیکن اب آپنے اپنی آدھی
‫problem دور پھینک دی.
‫لیکن اب بھی مجھے وہی problem حل
‫کرنی ہے -- یعنی Mike کا نام ڈھونڈنا.
‫لیکن اب book آدھی ہوگئی ہے کیونکہ
‫اب یہ M سے شروع ہوکر Z پر ختم ہوتی ہے.
‫>> لیکن یہی سب سے impressive بات ہے.
‫جس طرح جب ایک وقت میں آپ
‫میں سے آدھے لوگ بیٹھتے گئے،
‫اور ہر بار problem ادھے سے
‫ادھے سے آدھی ہوتی گئی.
‫بالکل اسی طرح، یہ problem
‫بھی آدھی ہوگئی ہے.
‫اور اب یہ 250 pages کی problem بن گئی ہے.
‫اور جیسے ہی میں نے کہ، oh، یہ تو
‫میں غلطی سے T والے section میں ہوں.
‫بہت آگے آگیا ہوں.
‫تو پھر میں phone book کے اس آدھے
‫حصّے کو بھی دور پھینک سکتا ہوں.
‫اب میں problem کو
‫ایک چوتھائی بنا دیا ہے.
‫>> اور یہ آپ بار کر سکتا ہیں،
‫جب تک آپ کے پاس، اصولاً،
‫صرف ایک page نہ رہ جاۓ.
‫اور Mike اگر اس page پر ہوگا، تو اس
‫problem کو اب میں solve کرسکتا ہوں.
‫لیکن کتنی دیر لگی مجھے اسے حل کرنے میں؟
‫پہلے والے case میں، مجھے شاید 1000
‫steps لگ گئے Mike Smith کو ڈھونڈے میں.
‫یعنی لگ جاتے -- اگر میں یہ
‫phone book اٹھا کر
‫ایک وقت میں ایک ایک
‫page کو چھان رہا ہوتا،
‫اور شاید پھر 1000 pages کے بعد
‫مجھے Mike مل جاتا.
‫>> دوسری والی approach میں
‫شاید مجھے 500 steps لگتے.
‫کیوں کہ میں دو دو pages
‫ایک ساتھ پلٹ رہا ہوتا.
‫لیکن یہ جو تیسری approach ہے
‫یہ نہایت ہی powerful ہے.
‫لیکن اب تھوڑا یہ دیکھتے ہیں کہ اس تیسری
‫approach میں ہم نے کیا کیا آخر.
‫اور یہ جو یہاں لکھی ہوئیں ہیں، ان میں سے
‫ہر ایک line کو میں statement (بیانیہ) کہونگا.
‫ایک phone book اٹھایئے
‫ Pick up a phone book
‫ فون book سے بیچ سے کھولیئے
‫ Open to the middle of the phone book
‫ ناموں کو دیکھیئے
‫ Look at names
‫اور اب آگے چیزیں تھوڑی سی دلچسپ
‫ہوجائیں گی، عقلی طور پہ،
‫لیکن پھر بھی بہت ہی simple.
‫ اگر تو Smith ان ناموں میں موجود ہے اس page پر
‫ If Smith is among the names
‫اس صورت میں پھر ہم شرطیہ طور پر ایک کام کرینگے.
‫یعنی ایک طرح سے ہمیں ایک فیصلہ کرنا ہے اب.
‫ Mike کو call کیجئے
‫ Call Mike
‫اگر Mike کا نام اس page کے ناموں میں موجود ہے،
‫تو Mike کو call کرلی ہم نے.
‫لیکن چوتھی line میں لکھا کام ہم صرف تب کریںگے
‫جب تیسری line سچ (true) ہو.
‫اور اس کا جواب ہے ہاں، یہ true ہے.
‫ ورنہ اگر Smith کا نام book کے پچھلے حصّے میں ہے
‫-- یعنی اگر میں M والے section میں ہوں،
‫ else if Smith is earlier in the book
‫اور اگر میں book کے left طرف  دیکھ
‫رہا ہوں، تو پھر مجھے ایک بہت ہی
‫ملتا جلتا کام کرنا چاہیئے.
‫پھر مجھے اس book کے left والے آدھے حصّے کو بیچ سے کھولنا چاہیئے
‫ open to the middle of the left half of the book
‫تو ہم left جائینگے ، اور وہاں سے
‫ دوبارہ step نمبر 2 دہرائیں گے
‫ go back to step 2
‫وہاں پر ناموں کو دیکھیں گے.
‫>> دوسرے الفاظ میں، ہم وہی کام کر رہے ہیں،
‫لیکن اب ہم نے problem کو آدھا کر دیا ہے.
‫ورنہ، پتہ ہے، کیا کرینگے؟
‫ ورنہ اگر سامنے کھلے ہوئے page کے مطابق
‫ اگر Smith کے بعد والے حصّے میں ہے book کے تو
‫ Else if Smith is later in the book
‫ اس book کے right والے آدھے حصّے کو بیچ سے کھولیئے
‫ open to the middle of the right half of the book
‫اور پھر  دوبارہ سے step نمبر 2 دہرائیے، ورنہ
‫ go back to step two, else
‫ایک چوتھی possibility بھی ہو سکتی ہے.
‫یا تو Mike یہیں ہے، یا پھر left پر ہے
‫یا پھر right پر ہے، یا کہیں ہے نہیں.
‫اور اس بارے ابھی ہی بات کرلینا بہتر ہے.
‫اور اگر واقعی میں کبھی آپ کا computer
‫crash ہوا ہے،
‫جو ہمیشہ تو نہیں لیکن کبھی کبھار ہو جاتا ہے، تو اس کی وجہ یہی
‫ہوتی ہے کہ programmer (یعنی software لکھنے والے بندے) نے
‫اس چوتھی والی possibility کے بارے میں
‫سوچا نہیں ہوتا.
‫اور اگر آپ اس طرح کے scenario کو
‫handle کرنے کیلئے code نہیں لکھیں گے،
‫تو آپ کو پھر اندازہ ہی نہ
‫ہو پائے کہ computer کیا کریگا.
‫اور دراصل program
‫crash بھی ہو سکتا ہے.
‫لیکن اس case میں نے اس کا دھیان رکھا ہے
‫اس لیے میں نے لکھا  ورنہ quit کردو (چھوڑ دو)
‫ else quit
‫کیوں کہ logically یہی چوتھا scenario
‫possible ہو سکتا ہے.
‫اب کچھ technical الفاظ کی
‫بات کر لیتے ہیں تاکہ پھر ہم
‫ان terms (الفاظ) کو سمجھ لیں، جو ویسے
‫تو ہم عام بول چال میں use کرتے ہیں.
‫وہ ساری چیزیں جن کو ابھی ابھی میں yellow
‫color میں highlight کیا ہے.
‫ان ہیں functions یا procedures کا نام دونگا.
‫یہ سب ایک طرح کے actions (عمل) ہیں.
‫یعنی pick up (اٹھاؤ)، open (کھولو)، look at (دیکھو)، call
‫(call کرو)، open (کھولو)، open (کھولو)
‫quit (چھوڑ دو) -- یہ سب actions ہیں جنہیں
‫Computer سائنس کی زبان میں ہم function کہیںگے.
‫>> ساتھ ہی yellow رنگ میں، میں نے
‫جن چیزوں کو highlight کی ہے
‫ان کو ہم conditions (شرائط) یا branches
‫(شاخیں) کہیںگے.
‫یہ فیصلہ لینے کے وہ points ہیں جہاں سے
‫آپ شاید یہاں آسکتے ہیں، یا پھر یہاں،
‫یا پھر کسی اور direction میں جا سکتے ہیں.
‫تو یہ سب conditions (شرائط) ہیں.
‫اور یہ والی تھوڑی سی fancy ہے.
‫ان سوالوں کو ہم Boolean Expression
‫(بُولییَن جملہ) کا نام دے دیتے ہیں،
‫جو  Bool نام کے ایک شخص کے نام  پر رکھا گیا ہے.
‫>> اور ایک Boolean جملہ
‫وہ ہوتا ہے جو کہ
‫یا تو سچ ہو یا جھوٹ، ہاں ہو یا نہ.
‫تو یہ ایک ایسا سوال ہوتا جس کا آپ کو چاہیئے
‫ہوتا ہے، تاکہ کسی condition کے بارے میں آپ
‫فیصلہ کر سکیں -- تاکہ جواب جاننے پر
‫آپ یا تو left یا right جاسکیں، یا پھر بالکل
‫کچھ اور کر سکیں.
‫>> اور پھر آخر میں یہ والی lines --
‫ step نمبر 2 پر واپس جاؤ
‫ go back to step 2
‫-- انکو ہم
‫مختلف طریقوں سے implement کر سکتے ہیں.
‫اور آپ میں سے جن لوگوں کو programming کی
‫ہوگی انہوں نے اس کو
‫ مختلف طریقے سے کیا یا سوچا ہوگا.
‫لیکن آج اتنا ہی کافی ہوگا کہ آپ
‫اس کے پیچھے کا idea سمجھ لیں.
‫یہ اصل میں ایک ایسی چیز کو
‫جنم دے رہا ہے جسے عام طور پر ہم
‫Loop (چکر) کہتے ہیں -- ایک طرح کا cycle،
‫کیونکہ یہ ایک ہی کام کو بار بار کروا رہا ہے.
‫>> تو اب ہم یہ دیکھتے ہیں کہ
‫یہ algorithm کتنے پانی میں ہے.
‫یہ بالکل صحیح algorithm ہے.
‫اگر Mike اس book میں ہے، تو یہ چار scenarios
‫(یعنی صورتیں) ہونگی -- اور ہم بار بار
‫لگاتار اس ڈھونڈنے کی کوشش کرینگے.
‫لیکن کتنے پانی میں ہے یہ algorithm؟
‫ہمیں بہت زیادہ تکلّف کرنے
‫کی ضرورت نہیں ہے
‫لیکن ہم کچھ x اور y کو plot
‫کرکے تھوڑا سا یہ
‫اس problem کی shape کو سمجھنے کی کوشش کرتے ہیں.
‫>> x-axis پر ہے problem کی size
‫اور y-axis پر ہے کہ اس کو
‫solve کرنے میں کتنا time لگا.
‫تو یہ شاید ہوسکتا ہے کہ total کتنے pages ہیں.
‫(یعنی x-axis: یعنی problem کا size)
‫اور یہ ہو سکتے ہیں کہ کتنے seconds لگے
‫یا کتنے pages پلٹنے پڑے
‫(یعنی y-axis)
‫اگرچہ، ہمیں یہ سمجھنا ہے کہ
‫یہ graph ہمیں کیا بتا رہا ہے.
‫اور اگر سب سے پہلے والی algorithm کو لیں،
‫تو اسکا میں کہونگا کہ وہ ایک سیدھی لکیر ہوگا.
‫اگر book میں pages کی تعداد n ہے تو
‫Mike کو ڈھونڈے کیلئے بھی ہم کو n
‫steps لینے پڑیں.
‫اگر کل کو Verizon یا کوئی اور phone
‫company ایک page اور add کردے book میں
‫تو  ہمیں بھی ایک اور step لینا پڑیگا --
‫ایک اور step لگےگا Mike کو ڈھونڈے میں.
‫تو one-to-one کا ratio ہے
‫(یعنی جتنے pages ہونگے اتنے ہی شاید پلٹنے پڑینگے)
‫یہ ایک سیدھی لکیر والا slope ہے.
‫>> جب کہ وہ جو دوسرا algorithm ہے
‫-- یعنی اگر میں
‫ایک ساتھ دو دو کر رہا ہوں --
‫2، 4، 6، 8، یعنی double --
‫ایک وقت میں دو دو pages کو
‫پلٹ رہا ہوں، تو
‫اب بھی یہ سیدھی لکیر ہی ہوگی.
‫لیکن اب یہ one-to-two کا ratio ہے،
‫(یعنی جتنے pages ہیں، اس کے آدھے پیجز پلٹنے پڑے)
‫جیسا کہ chart پر yellow میں دکھایا ہے،
‫اگر اتنے pages ہونگے تو،
‫مجھے پھر اتنے steps یا seconds
‫لگ جائیں گے.
‫ورنہ پھر مجھے اس سے double
‫steps لگیں گے، اس red line کے مطابق.
‫>> But the green line is the real takeaway.
‫اسے ہم عام طور پر (algorithm نہیں بلکہ) Logarithm
‫کہتے ہیں -- n کا log
‫جہاں n کا مطلب pages کی total تعداد ہے.
‫لیکن سب سے زیادہ اہمیت اس graph
‫کے shape کی ہے کیوں کہ فلحال
‫ہمیں ایک ایک point کی فکر کرنے کی ضرورت نہیں.
‫>> فرض کریں کہ ایک شدید صورتِ حال پیش آتی ہے.
‫فرض کرلیں کہ کل کو Verizon اپنی phone
‫book کے pages کی تعداد کو double کردیتی ہے،
‫یعنی 1000 سے 2000 صفحے.
‫تو پہلے والے algorithm میں شاید مجھے
‫steps looking for Mike, just because
‫Verizon doubled the size of the book.
‫The second algorithm-- it might
‫take me an extra 500 steps.
‫1,000 more pages, I go two at a
‫time-- 500 more steps to find Mike.
‫>> But that third algorithm
‫is kind of magical.
‫Verizon doubles the number
‫of pages from 1,000 to 2,000,
‫but how many more steps does
‫it take me to look for Mike?
‫It's just one, because I can just
‫tear the phone book one more time
‫from a 2,000 page problem to a
‫1,000 page problem, and voila.
‫I've taken a massive bite out of it.
‫>> And if you go really extreme,
‫suppose that the phone book
‫company had something crazy like
‫a 4 billion page phone book.
‫Well how many steps might it take
‫to find Mike Smith in a 4 billion
‫page phone book?
‫It's a big number, but just 4 billion to
‫2 billion to 1 billion to 500 million,
‫250 million-- still
‫sounds like big numbers,
‫but I'm very quickly
‫getting to smaller values.
‫>> And in fact, if I do the math
‫right, I can only divide 4 billion
‫by roughly 32 times before
‫I get down to just one.
‫So if that phone book were 4
‫billion pages long, no big deal.
‫Within a few seconds, maybe 32
‫seconds, I could divide it in half
‫and eventually find Mike or
‫conclude that he's not there.
‫And that's the essence of an
‫algorithm-- a good algorithm.
‫And that's one of the
‫goals of a class like this,
‫is trying to figure out how do I
‫solve the problem not just correctly,
‫like I always knew how to do it one
‫page at a time-- but correctly and well.
‫How do I design good
‫solutions to problems?
‫So let's take a moment here
‫and give you a sense now
‫of CS50 the course itself-- introduce
‫a few course's staff members.
‫Just before 2:00, we'll
‫take a short break
‫so that those of you
‫who are shopping can
‫duck out and take a
‫look at some other class
‫and watch the rest of this online.
‫But for now, let me introduce
‫CS50, the class itself,
‫and particularly what is new.
‫>> So the past spring, we
‫spent quite a bit of time--
‫the course's staff and I-- thinking
‫about what it is we want CS50 to be,
‫and going back to first
‫principles, so to speak,
‫to consider what it is we want
‫this course to look like and be
‫like for its students.
‫And so you'll see in problem
‫set zero as well, an invitation
‫to take a look at that
‫URL which summarizes
‫some of the motivations behind the
‫following characteristics of fall 2016.
‫>> So as you may have gleaned
‫from the TL:DR handout,
‫the syllabus today as well as from
‫the course catalog, this year in CS50,
‫you're only expected to attend
‫today-- so job well done--
‫and the last lecture on November 21st.
‫And you're welcome but not expected to
‫attend those lectures in the middle,
‫because what we're doing
‫this year, is shooting
‫in real-time the course's material.
‫So everything will stay
‫current and incorporated
‫as best we can-- current events
‫and conversations that folks might
‫be having in industry in the
‫world, but making that material
‫available, as a result, even earlier--
‫complete with full text transcripts
‫and searchability and
‫links to other resources.
‫>> And indeed, we've been
‫claiming for some time
‫and we do now believe this,
‫that we can create, digitally,
‫a more immersive, a more compelling
‫educational experience, as opposed
‫to gathering here some 23 times
‫in person, hearing someone like me
‫simply talk about computer science,
‫as opposed to engaging more actively.
‫So you'll see in the course's syllabus
‫a sketch of the semester here,
‫along with when lectures will
‫be filmed, to which you're
‫welcome but not expected,
‫and when they will
‫be released on the course's website.
‫>> And what we'll do here on
‫Wednesdays starting next week,
‫is a lot more intimately, with only
‫those folks who want to participate,
‫is a so-called walk through,
‫where I and the course's heads
‫will actually make things
‫a little more intimate
‫down here in the orchestra
‫section, still have some technology
‫and walk through the
‫current week's problem set,
‫and offer you particularly-- if among
‫those less comfortable-- all the more
‫guidance that you might want or
‫need for the week's challenge.
‫And similarly, for those who can't
‫attend those in person, no big deal.
‫There will be similarly led by
‫one of the course's senior staff,
‫Zamalya, the same opportunity embedded
‫in the problem sets themselves.
‫>> Problem sets this year
‫will be released on Fridays
‫and no longer do seven days later,
‫but 10 days later-- deliberately
‫overlapping with each problem
‫set, so as to better accommodate,
‫we hope, ebb and flow
‫in student schedules,
‫especially when midterms or athletics
‫or academics or extracurriculars
‫tend to come and go
‫especially mid-semester.
‫That should give you a little more
‫discretion as to whether you front
‫load your week with CS50 or back load
‫it on the following weekend instead.
‫So look to the course's syllabus
‫here for the schedule thereof.
‫And you'll notice too among
‫the changes this year,
‫for those more familiar with
‫programming in the past,
‫we'll start the semester as
‫we will today in Scratch,
‫focus especially on the language
‫called C, and then transition not
‫to PHP, but to a language called
‫Python towards the end of the semester
‫in the context of web programming,
‫along with SQL and JavaScript,
‫HTML, CSS, and yet more.
‫>> And in answer to an FAQ,
‫it's indeed the case
‫that CS is not as scary as I once
‫thought it was, but it is as much work
‫as I had heard it might be.
‫But this is the say that here are some
‫statistics from fall 2015 student body,
‫whereby the horizontal blue lines
‫represent the average number of hours
‫reported.
‫And you'll see an average of
‫six to 10 to 12-- maybe 16
‫or so and so forth, but with
‫high variance to be clear.
‫And so realize that there is not only
‫students more comfortable and less
‫comfortable in the course,
‫but a corresponding support
‫structure to get those students
‫through the semester successfully.
‫>> Indeed, in answer to an FAQ, should
‫you take CS50 as a first year?
‫Absolutely.
‫And in fact, I do regret
‫not having found my way
‫or found a new field
‫that first year as well.
‫And should you take CS50 with
‫other courses, certainly as well--
‫and the general advice we might
‫give students, that CS50's probably
‫not the kind of class or intro class
‫that you should take with three
‫other or four other p-set classes.
‫But if you're taking two other p-set
‫classes, something else, and CS50,
‫absolutely manageable.
‫I've had many students in the
‫past done so quite successfully.
‫>> And to get you toward that
‫finish line successfully,
‫does the course have sections--
‫different tracks for students
‫less comfortable, more comfortable,
‫and somewhere in between,
‫whereby in the course's
‫first problem set,
‫you'll be asked to describe yourself.
‫And if you are among those less
‫comfortable, it's the kind of thing
‫that you just rather know.
‫And indeed, that's been the
‫growing demographic in CS50
‫for quite a few years.
‫>> As of last fall for
‫instance, 58% of the class
‫described themselves as
‫among those less comfortable,
‫with 9% among those more
‫comfortable, and then
‫the other students there in
‫red describing themselves
‫as somewhere in between.
‫And you'll see here the topics overall
‫and schedule of sections, all of which
‫are offered in person, in
‫real time, with the course's
‫amazing staff of teaching fellows
‫and course assistants, some of whom
‫you'll meet in just a moment.
‫>> Sections themselves, as you'll see, will
‫be Mondays and Tuesdays and Wednesdays,
‫so as to allow you to dive
‫in after engaging, if you so
‫choose, in the course's
‫lecture earlier that week.
‫And then office hours, which
‫certainly, with each passing year,
‫have been no less of a
‫challenge for the course.
‫And this year, we're planning not
‫only to hold office hours-- one
‫on one opportunities for help for
‫students on Wednesdays Thursdays
‫and Sundays, the last of those
‫being in the afternoon by design
‫to reduce some of the stress that
‫invariably arises with late night
‫p-settting with a deadline looming--
‫but office hours will also be offered
‫on Mondays and Tuesdays and
‫Wednesdays, and Fridays and Saturdays,
‫thanks to our friends at HSA.
‫>> CS50 now has its own space
‫for students and CS50 staff,
‫atop 67 Mount Auburn Street,
‫right there in Harvard Square.
‫The vision for which is that CS50's
‫TFs and CAs throughout the week,
‫pretty much throughout most
‫days, will be there for support.
‫So if you've got some
‫question on a p-set
‫or you're feeling a little
‫blocked or a little confused,
‫and heck, you've got an hour or
‫half an hour between classes,
‫especially in the square-- can you
‫pop in and have that question answered
‫of have that confusion clarified--
‫very much in the spirit,
‫you're familiar, of the math
‫department's own math questions center,
‫but pretty much around the clock per
‫[? Gcal ?] that we will post online.
‫>> Tutoring is also available for those
‫students, freely from the course's
‫own staff if you would like
‫more intimate one on one,
‫or two or three classmates only, working
‫with one of the course's staff members.
‫And indeed, these here are just
‫some of the course's staff members,
‫a few of whom you'll
‫meet in just a moment.
‫In fact, CS50's own
‫head teaching fellow,
‫and head course
‫assistant, and preceptor,
‫could come on up, allow
‫them to say hello.
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫SPEAKER 1: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫SPEAKER 2: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫SPEAKER 3: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫>> DAVID MALAN: And allow us to
‫bring on board two of CS50's most
‫senior staff, Rob and Zamayla as well.
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫>> Indeed, both Rob and
‫Zamayla have been with us
‫for so long, that I was able
‫to go into CS50's archives
‫and find this very SD
‫footage of them participating
‫on stage themselves some years ago.
‫ROB: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫ZAMAYLA: [INAUDIBLE]
‫
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫DAVID MALAN: Thank you.
‫
‫So in addition to these
‫team members here,
‫CS50 has a team of nearly 100
‫staff members, all of whom
‫will be available for sections
‫and office hours and so much more.
‫And as Rob says too, this is
‫the most significant overhaul
‫of CS50 in the 10 years that
‫I've been in [INAUDIBLE].
‫[INAUDIBLE] focused especially
‫in providing a support structure,
‫trimming away a lot of
‫the bulk that's been
‫accumulated in 10 years
‫of iterative developments
‫on the course's problem sets.
‫>> So this year, not only in class but
‫also in the form of the course's problem
‫sets, should you find things to
‫be more streamlined, trimmer, much
‫more manageable than
‫in years past, as we
‫shed some of the baggage that's
‫developed by nature of evolving year
‫after year and iterating.
‫So the new and improved begins today.
‫>> You'll meet some more of the
‫course's staff out in the [INAUDIBLE]
‫at 2:30, where we serve,
‫as a tradition, cake.
‫There's a bit more cake
‫than that, but you'll
‫meet Erin and Tobias and others still.
‫And let me give you
‫a tour before we hear
‫from some of the other staff members
‫in the class, of what awaits as well.
‫In fact, we always start CS50's
‫semester this coming Saturday,
‫with what's called CS50 Puzzle Day.
‫>> It has nothing to do with
‫computer science per se,
‫but with about problem
‫solving more generally.
‫And if you so choose to partake,
‫per some of the invitations,
‫you might have seen door
‫dropped or on the stage here,
‫it's an opportunity in teams
‫of two or three or four,
‫to participate for puzzles and pizza
‫and prizes and more-- this Saturday,
‫stay tuned for more.
‫>> You'll find too that every
‫Friday, at Fire and Ice,
‫does CS50 bring a
‫whole bunch of students
‫to lunch, to make a large
‫class feel more intimate,
‫and generally bring together
‫alumni and friends from industry
‫to talk about what they've
‫been up to since graduating.
‫Similarly, this year, will we
‫inaugurate the first ever CS50 50
‫coding contest-- a mid-semester
‫opportunity to allow everyone
‫on an opt in basis, to have a
‫challenge of wits against classmates,
‫again in teams of two or three or
‫four, using only that programming
‫savvy that you then have under
‫your belt after just six or seven
‫weeks of the class, and participating
‫in this kind of competition
‫online-- if you'd like to hone your own
‫skills all the more in that challenge.
‫At the end of the semester is
‫the so-called CS50 Hackathon--
‫an opportunity that begins at 7:00
‫PM ends at 7:00 AM, and along the way
‫are 12 evening hours in which to dive
‫into the course's final project--
‫an opportunity to design and
‫implement most anything of interest
‫to you with your teaching
‫fellow's guidance.
‫Around 9:00AM do we typically
‫serve pizza, 1:00 AM,
‫Philippe's, and the few of us
‫who are still awake at 5:00 AM,
‫are shuttle bussed down the
‫road to IHOP for breakfast.
‫>> And then a few days later
‫is the so-called CS50 fare--
‫an end of semester exhibition in
‫celebration of just how far so many
‫of CS50 students have come from
‫week zero all the way to week ,
‫and keeping in mind that 73% of those
‫classmates and yours this year have
‫never taken a CS class before.
‫In fact, to reemphasize as much, here
‫is a few more faces from CS50's staff.
‫SPEAKER 4: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫SPEAKER 5: [INAUDIBLE].
‫SPEAKER 6: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫SPEAKER 7: [INAUDIBLE].
‫SPEAKER 8: [INAUDIBLE]
‫
‫SPEAKER 9: [INAUDIBLE].
‫>> SPEAKER 4: [INAUDIBLE].
‫>> SPEAKER 10: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫SPEAKER 11: [INAUDIBLE].
‫SPEAKER 12: [INAUDIBLE].
‫
‫SPEAKER 13: [INAUDIBLE]
‫>> SPEAKER 14: [INAUDIBLE].
‫>> SPEAKER 13: [INAUDIBLE].
‫SPEAKER 15: [INAUDIBLE]
‫
‫SPEAKER 16: [INAUDIBLE].
‫>> SPEAKER 11: [INAUDIBLE]
‫
‫SPEAKER 5: [INAUDIBLE].
‫DAVID MALAN: Some of the team
‫are themselves shopping classes.
‫But if those members
‫of CS50 staff are here,
‫could come on up for just a moment.
‫CS50's TFs and CAs and [? staff ?]
‫members here-- these are just a few
‫of the faces-- one of whom you just
‫saw, and a few other-- and a few others
‫still.
‫Why don't we go ahead and allow
‫you guys a five minute break.
‫If you need to duck out to
‫shop classes, that's fine.
‫And in five minutes, we'll resume,
‫taking a look at Scratch-- the first
‫of our programming language, meet
‫the course's staff here some more,
‫and focus ultimately
‫on problem set zero.
‫So we'll be back in five minutes.
‫>> All right.
‫So we are back.
‫And in our remaining
‫time today, the goal
‫is to level the playing field
‫in terms of some terminology,
‫in terms of some ideas.
‫Because indeed, as per
‫some of the charts earlier,
‫there is going to be a range of
‫levels of experience in the class,
‫some of whose students have
‫taken some programming before,
‫some of whom haven't.
‫And so with this first problem
‫set and with this first language
‫do we have an opportunity to start
‫to take for granted after today
‫some common vocabulary and idea.
‫>> And we'll do this by way of
‫the course's first languages--
‫in addition to C and Python and
‫JavaScript and SQL and HTML and CSS,
‫we'll be focusing initially
‫and just for problem set zero
‫on this graphical language, called
‫Scratch, developed by MIT'S Media Lab
‫down the road, to help
‫students and kids especially
‫express themselves algorithmically--
‫in a way more consistent with what
‫we might call computational thinking.
‫>> And it's a useful language because
‫very quickly next week in week one,
‫do we transition to a more
‫traditional and arcane language called
‫C, which is purely textual.
‫You only use your keyboard in
‫order to write instructions
‫like these on the screen.
‫But even if you've never seen
‫a programming language before,
‫in just glancing at
‫this, all be it cryptic,
‫you can probably guess that
‫probably prints Hello World.
‫But there's a lot of
‫syntactic overhead there.
‫There is the weird hash
‫symbol or hash tag up top.
‫There's the angle brackets, some
‫parentheses, curly braces, semi-colon--
‫there's just so much visual
‫syntax that gets in the way.
‫We start the course with
‫Scratch so as to get
‫past all of those intellectually
‫uninteresting distractions,
‫and focus instead on the ideas.
‫>> In fact, this might be before.
‫This, for this, week shall be after.
‫This, in this graphical
‫language Scratch,
‫is how you would implement that same
‫program-- a program that when run,
‫simply says hello world.
‫And what's nice about Scratch is
‫that it's this graphical programming
‫environment that uses puzzle pieces or
‫blocks, that only interlock together
‫if it makes logical sense to do so.
‫And with Scratch can you develop
‫animations and interactive games
‫and art, and any number of things that
‫you might imagine in your own mind,
‫and implement them simply by
‫dragging and dropping puzzle pieces.
‫>> And indeed, we'll have the ability
‫to express some of the same ideas
‫that I just mentioned a moment
‫ago in the context of Mike Smith
‫and searching a phone book-- things
‫like functions, just actions,
‫things like loops that do
‫things again and again,
‫variables, which is
‫something we'll introduce,
‫but it's familiar perhaps from
‫algebra-- just some kind of placeholder
‫to store some value you might
‫need later-- Boolean expressions,
‫where those yes no or true
‫false questions from before.
‫Conditions are those forks in the
‫road-- those branches so to speak.
‫And then there are some fancier
‫features we'll see even today,
‫called arrays and threads and
‫events, that we'll then revisit over
‫time in different languages.
‫But Scratch allows us
‫to explore all of these.
‫So here in Scratch, this purple
‫block is what a function is typically
‫going to look like.
‫This purple puzzle piece that has some
‫word like say, which is the action,
‫and then it might have an
‫argument or a parameter-- some way
‫of kind of customizing
‫what that block does
‫so that it's not pre-determined by
‫MIT what this purple block says.
‫In fact, you'll see in a
‫moment that I'm able to type
‫the words like hello world, or
‫hello David, or hello Zamayla,
‫or whatever I want, in the argument
‫to that puzzle piece-- the white box
‫there.
‫Meanwhile, if I want a loop, we'll
‫see that there's puzzle pieces that
‫look a little orange like this.
‫And their shape kind of suggests that
‫something happens again and again
‫in a cycle.
‫>> So if I wrap a say hello world block
‫with a forever block in Scratch,
‫it's just going to keep saying hello
‫world forever, quite literally.
‫Meanwhile, there's another
‫type of loop in Scratch
‫that we'll see-- a repeat
‫block-- where, if you
‫know in advance how many times
‫you want the loop to execute
‫a finite number of times in fact-- you
‫can specify that by typing in a number
‫or even plugging in a variable,
‫like x or y as we'll see.
‫>> In fact, variables like
‫i in this case, which
‫is a common name for an
‫integer variable that
‫just stores a number--
‫an integer might be,
‫to use this orange block here to
‫set a variable like i to zero.
‫Here's an example in green of a
‫Boolean expression in Scratch.
‫Even though this looks like a math
‫formula, math inequalities like this
‫really are Boolean expressions.
‫This is either true or false.
‫I is less than 50.
‫It's either a yes or no answer
‫or true or false answer.
‫And we'll generally call
‫those Boolean expressions.
‫And it doesn't have to be 50.
‫It can be x less than y,
‫greater than y, equal to y--
‫any number of other
‫questions might be asked.
‫>> Now, at first glance, this might look
‫suddenly quite bold here, and it is.
‫But concept wise, it's
‫pretty familiar from before.
‫If x is less than y, than say as much.
‫Else if x is greater
‫than y, then say as much.
‫Else say x is equal to y.
‫So we have an example
‫there of a third scenario--
‫the only third possibility-- x is either
‫greater than, less than, or equal to.
‫So we have a three way fork in the road.
‫>> And notice what's cool here-- Scratch,
‫it would seem, has just one puzzle
‫piece, in this case, in if else block.
‫And yet that would seem to imply you can
‫only have a two way fork in the road.
‫You can go left or right, but
‫what about that third scenario?
‫What if x equals y?
‫No big deal.
‫Take one puzzle piece, put
‫another one inside of it
‫to create the semantic equivalent
‫of if, else if, else-- and now you
‫have your three way fork in the road.
‫And as we'll see, the
‫Scratch puzzle pieces
‫can be stretched and grow, so
‫as to cram more stuff in them.
‫You don't have to fit
‫everything in its default size.
‫>> This is something we'll
‫soon see is called an array.
‫It's like a list-- some way of
‫storing multiple pieces of information
‫in a variable, not just a number.
‫These we'll see a representative of
‫something called multi-threading.
‫In fact, all of your
‫Macs and PCs these days
‫support multi-threading,
‫which means you can literally
‫do multiple things at a time.
‫You can have Microsoft Word up in the
‫foreground, working on some essay.
‫You might have a browser
‫in the background opening
‫G-mail or Facebook or the like.
‫Your computer can do multiple things
‫today because it is multi-threaded,
‫and programs they're in in
‫particular are also multi-threaded.
‫>> There's things called events as
‫well in the world of Scratch,
‫and then there's a way too, to make
‫our own custom puzzle pieces if things
‫don't actually exist in advance.
‫So let's motivate this as follows.
‫Some years ago, when I
‫first discovered Scratch,
‫when I was actually a
‫grad student at MIT, we
‫ourselves were tasked to make homework.
‫And I implemented--
‫which, in retrospect,
‫was a very poor decision because it's
‫the most infuriating song in the world
‫to listen to for eight hours
‫while working on your homework--
‫but something I had called Oscar Time,
‫which is perhaps a familiar song.
‫>> CS50s own Jordan Hayashi, one of
‫our more senior staff members,
‫has upgraded it for 2015 and
‫now 2016, since back in the day,
‫I had everything just going
‫into Oscar's trash can.
‫Now we support recycling and composting.
‫>> But to paint the picture
‫of what we can do here
‫and to motivate some of
‫the lower level examples,
‫could we get one other
‫volunteer to just come on up
‫and play my first
‫homework assignment ever?
‫Come on up.
‫What's your name?
‫>> HENRY: Henry.
‫>> DAVID MALAN: Henry, come on up.
‫Come on up.
‫Head either way, and
‫you'll see in a moment,
‫I'm going to go ahead and hit the
‫green flag in the top right hand
‫corner, which means go.
‫The little stop sign icon
‫is going to say stop,
‫and that's when you start
‫and stop the program.
‫Nice to meet you.
‫All right.
‫So we're going to see the instructions
‫on the screen in just a moment.
‫And just by playing this game
‫for a few seconds-- trust me,
‫we're not going to want to play
‫all the way to the end-- you will
‫get a sense of what the program does.
‫And more than just focus on Henry
‫being good or bad at this game, focus
‫and how was it implemented by me
‫originally and then by Jordan.
‫In other words, where are the variables?
‫Where are the loops?
‫Where are the functions?
‫And we'll see if we don't see
‫those underneath the hood.
‫>> Just click and drag trash
‫to the appropriate bin.
‫>> [MUSIC PLAYING]
‫All right.
‫That's very good.
‫Why don't we stop it there.
‫Thank you.
‫Congratulations to Henry.
‫>> [APPLAUSE]
‫>> Just imagine debugging that program.
‫If there's a problem two
‫minutes into the song-- but so
‫what's going on here really?
‫As complicated as it might
‫start to seem to get over time,
‫indeed more and more
‫stuff started falling,
‫what's interesting about
‫this kind of example--
‫and we'll see a few
‫others-- is that if you
‫look past the complexity or
‫the sophistication of the game,
‫there's a very simple building
‫blocks that play-- all of which,
‫if you distill them to those
‫building blocks, are very accessible
‫and implementable unto themselves.
‫For instance, it's
‫been some time, but I'm
‫pretty sure what I initially did when
‫making this game for the first time
‫was I completely like procrastinated.
‫I didn't focus at all on the
‫logic or the puzzle pieces,
‫I focused on the graphics and finding
‫the street post and the trash can
‫and all of that.
‫But those were requisite
‫ingredients at first.
‫And once I finished procrastinating and
‫laying out the overarching framework,
‫I decided, let me just make one
‫piece of trash fall from the sky.
‫And we'll see Scratch
‫supports things called
‫sprites-- characters that can
‫have different costumes on so they
‫look different.
‫>> And so I put a trash
‫costume on one such sprite.
‫And I just needed it
‫to fall from the sky.
‫And so it turns out, Scratch,
‫like most programming languages,
‫supports random numbers or
‫technically pseudocode random numbers,
‫so that by dragging and
‫dropping certain puzzle pieces,
‫I was able to have the trash
‫come from the left at first.
‫And then the next time it fell, from
‫the right and then from the middle.
‫And all the game did was just
‫have trash falling from the sky.
‫You couldn't point at it or click on it.
‫You couldn't open the trash can.
‫You couldn't do anything.
‫But it was a baby step
‫toward my ultimate vision.
‫>> And after that, I actually
‫implemented some kind
‫of sensing so that if you did click
‫and drag on the piece of trash
‫over the trash can, Oscar's
‫lid would open and close.
‫Nothing would happen to the trash, but
‫at least the lid would open and close.
‫So then check, step two of two.
‫And this is what's going to be
‫key in both problem set zero
‫and in programming more generally, is to
‫take these very deliberate baby steps.
‫Because not only does it allow you to
‫feel honestly accomplished much more
‫quickly-- it's the
‫worst thing in the world
‫to try to implement all of Oscar Time,
‫then hours later hit the green flag,
‫and nothing works as expected
‫because where do you even
‫begin to debug or to
‫troubleshoot that program?
‫It's just overwhelming.
‫>> And so truly embracing this idea
‫of taking steps-- baby steps again
‫and again-- building up
‫something that's, in the end,
‫really impressive and complex, but
‫at first, is not nearly as much so.
‫In fact, let's do this.
‫Let me go ahead and-- Scratch itself
‫exists on the web at Scratch.MIT.edu,
‫and you'll be told as
‫much again in problem
‫set zero, the specification for
‫which is already on CS50's website.
‫>> But this is what Scratch itself is.
‫And there's really just
‫three primary areas.
‫At the top left there
‫is the so-called stage.
‫This is Scratch.
‫The default costume is a cat.
‫And this is the rectangular world in
‫which you can move-- up, down, left,
‫right and some other stuff.
‫In the middle here are our categories
‫or our pallets of puzzle pieces,
‫and different colors
‫mean different things.
‫And if you poke around, you'll see
‫things like loops and conditions
‫and variables and other ingredients.
‫>> And then over here is the scripts area.
‫This is where I can drag and drop
‫those puzzle pieces to do things.
‫So let's do one such thing.
‫Let me go ahead and--
‫and I know where it is.
‫So I'm going to immediately click on
‫where I know things are ready to be,
‫but pointing and clicking and
‫poking around are inevitable.
‫So when green flag clicked,
‫what do I want to do?
‫I'm going to do this.
‫I'm going to drag this purple puzzle
‫piece, say hello for two seconds,
‫and let me zoom in.
‫>> And I'm going to change this
‫to be what I want it to be--
‫hello world for two seconds is fine.
‫Now, I'm going to click the
‫green flag, or if I really want,
‫I can full screen it and then come back.
‫It will just keep
‫everything in one window.
‫Green flag-- hello world.
‫All right.
‫Not all that interesting.
‫So let me go ahead and do this.
‫Let me try another one.
‫When green flag clicked-- let's
‫do something like a sound.
‫And notice that out of
‫the box for free you get
‫a cat sound, as is the default sprite.
‫So now let me go ahead and
‫hit the green flag now.
‫>> [MEOWING]
‫>> Aw.
‫That's adorable.
‫I'm programming.
‫So what have I done?
‫This is the equivalent of a program.
‫It's obviously super simple.
‫It didn't really take all that much
‫effort and MIT did most of the work,
‫but I have called a function.
‫I have used a function.
‫I've made some action, using just
‫that one purple puzzle piece.
‫>> Well, if I want to do
‫three meows in a row?
‫Let me go ahead and do two and three.
‫And notice that when you
‫hover nearby a puzzle piece,
‫a little white line appears
‫sort of magnetically,
‫and it will snap
‫together when you let go.
‫Let's see what happens here.
‫>> [MEOWING]
‫
‫>> There's a bug.
‫I only hear one meow.
‫Why might that be?
‫Yeah?
‫Yeah.
‫We don't really hear it,
‫but that's good intuition.
‫They're all playing at the same time.
‫Why?
‫Well, the computer is just going
‫to do what you tell it to do.
‫So if you say, play sound,
‫play sound, play sound,
‫but you don't tell it to play until
‫you're done, play until you're done,
‫it's going to blow through
‫the program really fast
‫and do only what you tell it to do.
‫>> So I actually need to fix
‫this in a couple of ways.
‫I could just do this, get rid of this.
‫Let me try this other puzzle
‫piece-- play sound meow until done,
‫and then drag three of
‫these and click Play.
‫>> [MEOWING]
‫>> It's not really very--
‫thank you-- very natural.
‫So why don't I-- let
‫me go to control here.
‫Nice.
‫Wait one second, and now let me go back
‫to sounds, and play sound until done,
‫and then let me get wait one second.
‫And then let me go and get one
‫more sound, and here we go.
‫>> [MEOWING]
‫>> A little more natural, but
‫this is not very efficient.
‫Like I was getting bored, all be
‫it briefly, clicking back and forth
‫and really duplicating my work--
‫pretty much copying and pasting.
‫Indeed, if I Control
‫clicked or right clicked,
‫I could have just copied and pasted.
‫What would be a better construct to use?
‫What idea from before?
‫>> Yeah, so a loop.
‫And in fact, if we poked around,
‫we might find exactly that.
‫Let me go to Events or rather Control.
‫So repeat-- I don't
‫want it to be 10 times.
‫That's going to get annoying quickly.
‫But I will repeat three times.
‫Let me go back to sound and
‫play the sound until it's done.
‫Let me go back to Control
‫and just wait one second.
‫And notice, you might
‫think it doesn't fit,
‫but again if magnetically you let it
‫snap in place, it will grow to fill.
‫What's it play now?
‫>> [MEOWING]
‫OK.
‫Nice.
‫And this is what would be called
‫a program that's also correct.
‫It meowed three times fairly
‫naturally, but it's better designed.
‫I'm using less redundancy.
‫I didn't copy and paste anything.
‫I just used a better idea.
‫>> Now, this is still not all that
‫interesting with Scratch not doing
‫anything.
‫So let's do something else instead.
‫Let's do something forever.
‫And you know what?
‫Motion seems interesting.
‫Let's have him move 10
‫steps and hit play now.
‫>> OK.
‫Well we can kind of drag
‫him back, and he's still
‫running because he's doing this forever.
‫So the loop is doing
‫what it's saying to do,
‫but this isn't all that interesting.
‫Let's do this.
‫Let me add a control block, and use one
‫of those conditions for the first time.
‫>> So it's going to move 10 steps--
‫10 dots, 10 pixels on the screen--
‫then it's going to ask this question.
‫If something is true, then do
‫something inside this block.
‫So it turns out sensing has a whole
‫bunch of Boolean expressions--
‫questions of the yes no or true
‫false form-- let me do this.
‫>> If touching-- and then there's
‫this little drop down menu.
‫I can parameterize it.
‫If touching the edge-- let's
‫do something like that.
‫So if touching edge--
‫let me go back to motion.
‫And why don't we just
‫turn around 180 degrees?
‫All right.
‫So forever, move 10 steps.
‫If you're touching the
‫edge, turn 180 degrees.
‫And that's not the end of the program
‫because you're in a forever block,
‫so it's going to go again and
‫again and again and again.
‫So let's see what happens.
‫OK.
‫A little buggy, but kind of cool.
‫>> And we can add to this some silly things
‫that aren't all that intellectually
‫interesting.
‫But if we hit this little
‫microphone button-- ouch.
‫Let me clean this up.
‫Let me enhance this as
‫they would say on TV.
‫Clean that up, Save, and
‫now go up to scripts.
‫>> And now, let me go to sound.
‫Let me give it a name.
‫I'll call this ouch.
‫And now play sound ouch.
‫Notice it appears in the
‫little drop down menu.
‫Let's see.
‫>> [OUCH]
‫>> [LAUGHING]
‫But we can change t his on the fly.
‫We can be twice as annoying.
‫>> [OUCH]
‫>> Or if we make it like
‫1,000 steps at a time--
‫
‫>> OK.
‫So we're going to leave that one alone.
‫So again, building blocks-- I
‫started with something super simple,
‫and then I added a feature,
‫added a feature, added a feature.
‫And I no longer need to worry about
‫how the first of those features
‫was implemented as I continue
‫to layer things on top.
‫So in fact, let me do one other here.
‫Let me go ahead and open a file that
‫I brought in advance, called Sheep.
‫>> So it has a slightly different
‫character that looks like this.
‫And let me see if I can't
‫do something using a counter
‫in this case-- a so-called variable.
‫I'm going to go ahead and under Events--
‫let me get a green flag clicked.
‫Then let me go to Data, which I know
‫from just playing around before,
‫is where variables are.
‫And I'm going to go ahead and drag this.
‫>> So a variable called counter, and
‫I'm going to initialize it to zero.
‫I can call it anything-- x or
‫y or z-- but in programming,
‫calling something in a semantically
‫useful way, like counter,
‫that describes what it is, it's a
‫lot easier to read your code later.
‫Let me go ahead and get
‫a forever block here.
‫And let me go to the looks
‫page and do a Say block.
‫But what's cool about variables is I
‫don't have to just type in something
‫like hello world, which we've already
‫done, I can instead go to Data
‫and drag my variable, and even
‫though the shape doesn't quite
‫look like it should fit,
‫it will grow to fill.
‫And I'll just say the counter for one
‫second-- spoiler-- he's going to count.
‫We'll say it for one second.
‫Then I'm going to go and
‫have him wait for one second,
‫so it doesn't count up too fast.
‫And then lastly, change counter
‫by one-- in other words,
‫increment the counter by one
‫additional value and do this forever.
‫>> So the sheep too, like a
‫programmer, counts from 0.
‫
‫And if we wait long enough,
‫he will do this forever.
‫But that's not exactly true, because
‫in fact, as we'll discover in week one,
‫integers and computers more generally,
‫technically have only a finite-- well,
‫rather computers, when
‫they represent integers,
‫only have a finite number of bits.
‫Those light bulbs there
‫can only count so high
‫before you're out of light bulbs.
‫And a computer too,
‫only has so much memory,
‫only has so many transistors,
‫so it can only count so high.
‫>> So it turns out that the sheep,
‫I think, can count to 2 billion
‫or something pretty big.
‫So we're not going to
‫wait for this to happen.
‫But eventually some bug will happen
‫that can have some very real world
‫ramifications.
‫But beyond the sheep, that
‫just introduces a variable.
‫Let's go ahead and open up
‫something I made in advance
‫here called Pet the Cat--
‫Pet the Cat over here.
‫And notice here it's few
‫blocks, but when green flag
‫clicked, forever doing the following.
‫If you're touching the mouse
‫pointer-- so the cursor on the screen,
‫the arrow-- play sound meow
‫and then wait two seconds.
‫And just do this forever.
‫Just constantly wait
‫to see if the pointer--
‫if the cat is touching the pointer.
‫>> So I hit play.
‫Nothing's happening.
‫But as I move the cursor over the cat,
‫>> [MEOWING]
‫>> And if I move it away, not
‫petting the cat anymore.
‫So some conditional logic
‫nested inside of a loop.
‫How about this example, deliberately
‫called Don't Pet the Cat?
‫What's this going to do?
‫>> [MEOWING]
‫>> Why should you not pet the cat?
‫>> OK.
‫So this is an example of an if else.
‫It's a decision point and
‫because it's sitting in the loop,
‫they're both getting checked.
‫Is this true?
‫
‫And eventually, one of
‫those is going to apply
‫and so you hear either the meow or
‫the roar of the lion in that case.
‫>> Well, let's do a slightly more fancy one
‫that I made in advance too-- threads.
‫So a thread is just one
‫thing that a computer can do.
‫So a multi-threaded program is a program
‫that can do multiple things at once.
‫And all of these examples
‫thus far have had
‫just one script, so to speak--
‫one program like this up here.
‫But notice this program has
‫two sprites, two characters.
‫One is a bird.
‫One is a cat.
‫>> And notice when I click on these down
‫left, they each have their own scripts
‫or programs associated with them.
‫And both of those
‫programs, notice, start
‫with when green flag clicked--
‫let's look at the cat--
‫when green flag clicked.
‫And so indeed, when I hit play now,
‫two things are going to happen at once.
‫The cat and the bird are both
‫going to operate simultaneously
‫to create this effect.
‫And you might imagine what's happening.
‫There's a loop and the bird
‫and the cat are in a loop.
‫The bird is just bouncing like
‫I was before when I said ouch.
‫But the cat clearly has an advantage.
‫There's another sensing block
‫that points the cat deliberately
‫to the bird in this case here.
‫So we could tease apart, by looking
‫through those blocks, what's happening.
‫But the key ingredient here is one.
‫The bird, so that this game isn't
‫completely boring-- or this animation--
‫starts at a random direction.
‫And the computer is picking
‫a number between 90 and 180
‫essentially, so that it's a slightly
‫different animation each time.
‫>> And then notice here, if the
‫cat is touching the bird, then
‫play the lion four sound-- the roar.
‫But meanwhile in the bird's
‫palette, we have this.
‫Forever, if not touching the cat,
‫just keep moving three steps.
‫And then here's another puzzle piece.
‫If you're on the edge, bounce.
‫So the bird is just kind of
‫minding its own business,
‫just flying around and
‫bouncing, and it's really
‫the cat that had the conditional logic
‫to determine if it had caught the bird.
‫All right.
‫So let's do one other here,
‫this one being called Hi Hi Hi.
‫And this one here just does
‫this in a forever loop.
‫But notice-- how do we stop
‫this very annoying program?
‫
‫Hit the space bar.
‫Because if I do that,
‫the left hand program--
‫notice it's constantly listening--
‫is the key space press.
‫If the space bar pressed,
‫and if so, what does it do?
‫It does a very common technique.
‫It sets a variable equal to some value.
‫But it toggles that value.
‫[? So appearance ?]
‫based on the shape-- I
‫have a variable that I
‫wrote in advance called
‫Muted, which just says yes or no.
‫Is the sound muted or not?
‫True or false?
‫And notice, I'm saying this-- if
‫muted is zero, then change to one,
‫else set mute it to zero.
‫So just flip the value from zero to one.
‫I could have done-- change it
‫from two to three and three to two
‫or four to five or four to six.
‫But it doesn't matter
‫what numbers I use,
‫so long as I keep
‫changing it the opposite.
‫>> And most any programmer would just
‫choose zero and one-- false and true,
‫off and on-- to represent this.
‫And this is still running.
‫If I hit the space bar again
‫>> [SEAL SOUNDS]
‫>> The program is still running.
‫Because there's this other script
‫that says, forever do the following.
‫
‫If the muted variable equals
‫zero-- so if you're not muted
‫is the logic-- if it's false
‫or no, then play the sound,
‫because you're not muted.
‫You should play the sound and then
‫think hi hi hi for two seconds
‫and then wait, and do it
‫again and again and again.
‫>> And so in this way do we have a way for
‫people to-- for programs to interact.
‫And they don't have to
‫be as dated as others.
‫In fact, poking around--
‫no pun intended--
‫someone spent a huge amount of
‫time on the internet implementing
‫PokemonGo in Scratch.
‫It even geolocates you in
‫Cambridge or Allston here.
‫So if you want to see too what people
‫can do is this-- very fancy menu.
‫Click on here.
‫>> This is me with my arrow keys now.
‫I'm going to go after this.
‫Click.
‫
‫And now you click the PokeBall.
‫I mean, I think you're
‫supposed to click the PokeBall.
‫All right.
‫So I did that.
‫I can go over here.
‫And this person implemented some more
‫PokeBalls over here-- three PokeBalls.
‫>> We'll post a link to this
‫online so you can play.
‫But notice there's just
‫some basic building blocks.
‫It looks a lot fancier, and it is.
‫This is impressive and more
‫than we would typically
‫expect, certainly for problem set zero.
‫I have no idea how long
‫this person spent online.
‫But it's all just a loop.
‫There's a sound playing.
‫There's some kind of loop
‫listening for whether I'm
‫hitting the up arrow or the down
‫arrow or the left and the right,
‫and then if so, it's moving
‫it some number of pixels.
‫And then if I click on
‫another sprite, there's
‫some kind of if condition there.
‫Yeah, this is getting too intense.
‫We're going to stop.
‫It's all those basic building blocks.
‫There are no other ingredients other
‫than the ones we've looked at already.
‫>> And yet here, let me do
‫one final set of examples
‫that paints a picture too
‫of what you can do here.
‫Here's a very simple program that
‫just does this-- cough, cough, cough.
‫And based only on what
‫we've looked at thus far,
‫where is the obvious
‫opportunity for improvement.
‫This program is correct.
‫It coughs three times,
‫which is what I intended.
‫But it's poorly implemented.
‫It's badly designed.
‫Why?
‫Yeah.
‫It's not a loop.
‫And it's not so much
‫that it's not a loop,
‫it's that there's a lot of redundancy.
‫There is copied and
‫pasted code, so to speak.
‫And the solution probably
‫is indeed a loop.
‫So let me go ahead
‫and improve upon that.
‫And I'm going to drag these over here.
‫Let me go ahead and get a repeat
‫block, change this to three.
‫I'm going to throw away
‫some of those blocks.
‫>> And you'll notice it's pretty intuitive.
‫You drag and drop and things
‫appear and disappear eventually.
‫And I can just drag this in here, and
‫now I have a cleaner version still.
‫But you know what?
‫There's this opportunity
‫now for abstraction--
‫to start to define new vocabulary
‫that MIT didn't anticipate.
‫There's wait and repeat
‫and forever and if,
‫but what if I want to introduce
‫the word cough as a block?
‫What if I want a puzzle piece
‫whose purpose in life is to cough?
‫>> Well, let's look at this version
‫here, which I made as follows.
‫Magically, I have created
‫this puzzle piece here,
‫which Scratch allows you to do.
‫And indeed C and Python
‫and JavaScript are
‫going to allow you to do this as well.
‫You can create your own custom
‫pieces that you call what you want.
‫In this case, cough feels
‫like a reasonable definition.
‫And then with these pieces down
‫here can you define what it means.
‫>> I dragged and dropped from
‫this palette here-- more
‫blocks-- this big purple
‫block, where I typed in cough
‫as the name of my new puzzle piece.
‫And then I'm saying any time a user
‫calls this new cough puzzle piece,
‫do a say and a wait.
‫And so up here in my repeat block,
‫I can just cough three times.
‫>> And I would argue, especially
‫if now you hide this detail.
‫Who cares how cough is implemented?
‫All I care about as a
‫programmer that I can cough.
‫I don't care how say is implemented.
‫I just care that the
‫cat can say something.
‫I can abstract away that detail and
‫only focus on what's on the screen here.
‫But I can take this one step further.
‫>> Notice that here, I have
‫implemented the loop three times.
‫But what if instead I grab this version?
‫And what if instead
‫in this version here,
‫I just change my puzzle piece to take
‫an argument and input unto itself?
‫And that input can be
‫a number like three.
‫So now, if I am writing a program
‫and I want the cat to cough,
‫I can actually tell the puzzle
‫piece how many times to cough,
‫because at the bottom here, a fancier
‫version of these custom puzzle pieces
‫lets me specify that
‫cough actually takes
‫an input-- takes an argument like this.
‫And you know what?
‫Maybe I realize, wait a minute.
‫Coughing is the same--
‫it's fundamentally
‫the same idea as sneezing.
‫It's just a different
‫word on the screen.
‫I can abstract away
‫further and implement
‫this final version of a
‫cough, which at first glance
‫is way more complex looking.
‫But notice what I've done.
‫I have now generalized-- genericized
‫really-- this puzzle piece
‫to be called say word n times.
‫>> And now I have two new puzzle pieces
‫down here define cough n times.
‫And what does the cough function do?
‫What does my custom puzzle piece do?
‫It just calls the say block,
‫passing in the word I want to say,
‫passing in the number
‫of times I want to say.
‫Because now I can implement
‫sneeze by simply saying achoo,
‫in this case, some number of times.
‫>> And so I'm layering and layering.
‫And again, the key here is not
‫how I implemented it, but the fact
‫that if I just literally
‫move these off the screen,
‫look how simple if not
‫pretty my program now looks.
‫Because it does what it
‫says, I've abstracted
‫away what is inside that black box.
‫it happens to be a purple box here,
‫but I've obstructed away what's inside
‫because I don't care how it works.
‫I just care now that it works.
‫>> And indeed, in problem
‫set zero, this is exactly
‫the kind of layering of ideas you'll
‫have the opportunity to explore.
‫It's exactly the opportunity to
‫apply problem solving techniques,
‫to what's probably an
‫unfamiliar environment.
‫And whether you've not programmed
‫before or programmed before,
‫you'll find that there's
‫a little something
‫in this environment for everyone.
‫And with problem set
‫one in a week's time,
‫we'll be transitioned to focusing
‫on a higher level language called
‫C-- or rather a lower
‫level language called
‫C-- that's even more
‫powerful, even though it's
‫a little more cryptic at first glance.
‫>> And you'll realize per today's TL:DR,
‫that this problem set has a shorter
‫window of time than future ones, simply
‫because you should find it fairly
‫accessible.
‫And not to worry if
‫you add the class late.
‫We'll address that before long.
‫And before we adjourn for cake, let's
‫finish with just a two-minute look
‫at what awaits you here in CS50.
‫
‫[MUSIC PLAYING]
‫All right.
‫That's it for CS50.
‫We will see you soon.
‫Cake is now served.
‫
‫[MUSIC PLAYING]
‫SPEAKER 17: Have you heard
‫of a sabbatical, Chief?
‫
‫SPEAKER 18: Perhaps there's
‫more under the hood.
‫```